<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An historical treatise of the travels of Noah into Europe containing the first inhabitation and peopling thereof. As also a breefe recapitulation of the kings, governors, and rulers commanding in the same, even untill the first building of Troy by Dardanus. Done into English by Richard Lynche, Gent.</title>
            <title>Auctores vetustissimi. English. Selections</title>
            <author>Nanni, Giovanni, 1432?-1502.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1601</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 197 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 56 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06631</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17092</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108996</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844647</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844647</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9480</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06631)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9480)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 850:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An historical treatise of the travels of Noah into Europe containing the first inhabitation and peopling thereof. As also a breefe recapitulation of the kings, governors, and rulers commanding in the same, even untill the first building of Troy by Dardanus. Done into English by Richard Lynche, Gent.</title>
                  <title>Auctores vetustissimi. English. Selections</title>
                  <author>Nanni, Giovanni, 1432?-1502.</author>
                  <author>Linche, Richard.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[112] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Adam Islip,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1601.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of selections from: Nanni, Giovanni. Auctores vetustissimi.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-O⁴.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The travels of Noe into Europe.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf and the last leaf are blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>History, Ancient --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Europe --  History --  To 476 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9480:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9480:1"/>
            <p>AN HISTORICAL TREATISE OF THE TRAVELS OF <hi>NOAH</hi> INTO Europe: Containing the firſt inhabita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and peopling thereof.</p>
            <p>As alſo a breefe recapitulation of the Kings, Governors, and Rulers comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in the ſame, even untill the firſt building of Troy by <hi>Dardanus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Done into Engliſh by <hi>Richard Lynche,</hi> Gent.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Tempo è figlinola di verita.</hi>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <q>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </q>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by Adam Iſlip. 1601.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:9480:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9480:2"/>
            <head>To the Worſhipfull my very good and Maiſter <hi>Peter Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>auile.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ir, being wholly unfur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht of any other means to teſtifie my grateful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for your many kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes towards mee, and thinking it unfit that they ſo long ſhould ſleepe obſcured or publickly unacknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, I judged it irrequiſit by dedicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of theſe few lines unto you (diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled by Fortune for anie other faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) to let you know how much I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be found thankefull to an aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red friend. The matter handled, chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lengeth no great worth, the manner
<pb facs="tcp:9480:3"/>
in the dreſsing of it leſſe, and yet my endevors to deſerve the continuation of your love, not to bee rejected: as Time ſhall beget a more oportune occaſion, my induſtrie ſhall not ſlacke to apprehend the ſame, from which (it may be) may bee produced a better-ſhaped iſſue: till when and ever af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter I reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in all ſincere affection and fidelitie, aſſured, <hi>Richard Lynche.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:9480:3"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> A TREATISE OF the travailes of <hi>Noah</hi> into Europe, containing the firſt inhabitation and peopling thereof.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O begin vvith the genealogie of <hi>Dardanus</hi> (the firſt founder and erecter of the citie of Troy) it is requiſite that we take for our cheefeſt guide therein the firſt prince and Patriarch of the world, called <hi>Noe,</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Gallus;</hi> following herein moſt eſpecially, the chronicle of that au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenticke writer, <hi>Beroſus</hi> the Chaldean: who indeed of all others moſt accordeth with the writings and holy workes of <hi>Moyſes</hi> in the old Teſtament; for as much as the Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deans generally addicted themſelves to letters: unto which they were allured and perſuaded by <hi>Noe,</hi> ſhewing them the uſe of Hiſtorie, and therein the true particulars of the creation of the world, untill that very time wherein they then lived; which alſo <hi>Noe</hi> himſelfe learned and was
<pb facs="tcp:9480:4"/>
inſtructed in by his father <hi>Lamech,</hi> who likewiſe received his knowledge from his grandfather the Prophet <hi>Enoch,</hi> before hee was tranſported into the heavenly Paradice: and this <hi>Enoch</hi> had it by tradition from the firſt father <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> who was poſſeſt therewith by divine inſtinct and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inſpiration. Let us now therefore attend what this <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſus</hi> the Chaldaean will deliver unto us, being a moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned, auncient, and grave author, who flouriſhed not long before the times of <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great; and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whom (as <hi>Plinie</hi> in his Naturall hyſtorie reporteth) the Athenians for his great wiſdome and eloquence, erected in their univerſitie a moſt ſtately and gorgeous ſtatue to his owne ſhape and ſimilitude, whoſe tongue they guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded over with moſt pure and reſplendent gold. This <hi>Bero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> wee will in this Treatiſe much relie upon, adjoyning withall unto his authoritie other authors of great worth, learning, and antiquitie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Noe</hi> (according to S. <hi>Ierome</hi> in his interpretations of Hebrew words) ſignifieth as much as reſting or eaſing of a mans ſelfe; and he was the ſonne of <hi>Lamech,</hi> which ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth humilitie. This <hi>Noe</hi> by the deſcriptions of old writers was taken in thoſe daies to be a Giant, in reſpect of his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarie ſtature, proportion, and corpulencie: and he was about the age (as <hi>Moyſes</hi> alſo in the ſixt chapter of Geneſis affirmeth) of five hundred yeares, when he begat of his vile <hi>Ty<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> (otherwiſe called <hi>Aretia</hi>) theſe his three firſt ſonnes, <hi>Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> which interpreted, ſignifies famous, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe called <hi>Melchiſedech: cham</hi> the ſecond (though <hi>Beroſus</hi> affirme him to bee the youngeſt) which ſignifies ſubtiltie or craft: and <hi>Iaphet,</hi> which ſignifies libertie or freedome: with theſe his three ſonnes, <hi>Noe</hi> and his familie
<pb facs="tcp:9480:4"/>
lived in a citie called Enos, which was the firſt citie in the world, and was built by <hi>Cain</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Adam,</hi> at the foot of the mountaine Libanus in the land of Syria, and in the particular province of Phoenicia, not far from the famous citie of Ieruſalem, ſituated in the holy land.</p>
            <p>In this citie of Enos, and in many others thereabouts, inhabited and lived many moſt deformed, fierce, and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible giants, who by reaſon of their unmatchable ſtrength and indomitable powerfulneſſe, ruled and overſwaied all thoſe people thereabouts at their pleaſure, committing many odious and ungodly deeds, and living a moſt diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute and vicious life, engorging their luxurious appetites with ſurfets of adulterie and libidinous converſation, as void of ſhame, the law of nature, and the feare of God.</p>
            <p>In theſe times many very learned Aſtronomers and wiſe Soothſaiers gave out propheticall divinations of the ſuddaine approching deſtruction of the univerſall world, which their forewarning prognoſtications they engraved and cut forth in pillars of marble and ſtonie monuments, to ſignifie thereby unto the world, their knowledge of ſuch future and ſure happening accidents. All this notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, theſe obſtinat and heart-hardened Giants per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevered in their impious and deteſtable practiſes, tyranni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing and oppreſſing without all meaſure, addicting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the finding out of weapons, ſhields, and other warlick accouſtrements, as alſo to the making of tents, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilions, and ſuch like expedient neceſſaries for the field: wholly excluding all thoughts of any alteration or chaunge to enſue: onely the good giant <hi>Noe,</hi> among all the reſt, feared God, and was obedient to his lawes, with all the reſt of his familie and houſhold, which was <hi>Titea</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:9480:5"/>
his wife, <hi>Sem, Cham,</hi> and <hi>Iaphet,</hi> their children, and <hi>Pando<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra, Noela,</hi> &amp; <hi>Noegla,</hi> their wives: all which, <hi>Noe</hi> inſtructed in modeſtie and good manners, and in the reverence and feare of their ſoveraign Creator. He therefore, as well by divine commandement, as by the ſcience of Aſtronomie, by which he gathered the overthrow and confuſion of the world, began to frame and faſhion that huge ſhip or Ark, which we ſo often read of in holy ſcriptures, &amp; which was appointed from above to be the meanes of the ſalvation and preſervation of humane kind. <hi>Noe,</hi> when hee ſaw this generall inundation to approch and ſhew it ſelfe, convei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him and his familie into this Arke, when preſently all the world, and all things elſe therein (this excepted) were overwhelmed and ſubverted under the raging furie of this ſo ſtrange and all-devouring deluge: and this was perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med on the eighteenth day of Aprill, in the ſix hundred yeare of the age of <hi>Noe.</hi> And hetherto was accounted the firſt age of the world, according as <hi>Philo</hi> the Iew in his computations affirmeth.</p>
            <p>The world thus univerſally drowned and kept downe under the all-ſubduing power of the waters (<hi>Noe</hi> and his familie excepted) in the end they began againe to ſinke backe and retire into the earth, which when <hi>Noe</hi> percea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved (his Arke then reſting on the top of the high hill Gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicus in Armenia) by the will and commaundement of God, he with the reſt (which were ſeven) came out of his ſhip, and deſcended downe unto the new-dried land: which was performed eight hundred thirtie three yeares before the foundation of Troy, &amp; before the incarnation of Chriſt two thouſand three hundred and ſeventeene yeares. <hi>Noe</hi> then ſeeing himſelfe thus left the ſole King,
<pb facs="tcp:9480:5"/>
Monarch, Emperour, Patriarke, Lord, and Maiſter of the whole univerſall land, remained wonderouſly aſtonied at this ſo ſtraunge and ſence amazing accident: and paſſing along the land, he found on a plaine a faire pillar of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, whereon he carefully engraved and ſet downe the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luge and generall inundation of the world in the form of an hyſtoricall diſcourſe: &amp; this ſtone (as it is reported) is called at this day by the inhabitants thereabouts, <hi>Myri-Adam,</hi> which interpreted, ſignifies the iſſue of <hi>Noe;</hi> and it ſtandeth in the countrey of Armenia, beeing a great province in Aſia the great, which affronteth towards the Eaſt the Hyrcanian ſea, towards the South lies Meſopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamia, towards the North Colchos and Albania, and towards the Weſt, Cappadocia; and through the midſt of it runne the two famous rivers, Tigris and Euphrates, of all which countries, hereafter in this hyſtorie more at large ſhall be ſpoken. It is written, That <hi>Noe</hi> begat of his wife <hi>Tytea</hi> after the floud, thirtie children, <hi>viZ. Tuyſcon</hi> the Giant, <hi>Prometheus, Iupetus, Macrus,</hi> and the ſixteen <hi>Titans</hi> which were all Giants: alſo <hi>Cranus, Granaus, Oceanus,</hi> and <hi>Tipheus;</hi> and of daughters, <hi>Araxa</hi> ſurnamed the Great, <hi>Regina, Pandora, Crana,</hi> and <hi>Thetis:</hi> ſome authours doe alleadge more, but for brevities ſake wee will not fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther contend with others opinions. <hi>Noe</hi> thus living in Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menia, inſtructed theſe his children in the knowledge of ſacred Theologie, and in rites belonging to religion and holy ſacrifices, as alſo in the underſtanding of human ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and ſecreſies of Nature, of which hee himſelfe had compoſed many bookes, which afterward the prieſts and churchmen of Scythia and Armenia, preſerved and kept a great regard and reverence. For this cauſe he was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb facs="tcp:9480:6"/>
among the Scythians <hi>Ogyges Saga,</hi> which interpreted from the Scythian language, ſignifies as much as, Great Patriarke, ſoveraigne Prieſt, and mightie Sacrificer. And this <hi>Beroſus</hi> affirmeth, ſaying: <hi>Primum itaque dixerunt O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gygam Sagam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Beroſus.</note> 
               <hi>id eſt, Illuſtrem ſacrorum Pontificem Noam:</hi> he alſo taught and inſtructed them the knowledge of the courſe of the planets, and devided the yeare into twelve months, according to the courſe and circumference of the Moone: he alſo by his ſtudie of Aſtronomie and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervance of the coeleſtiall motions, could prognoſticat of the alterations of weather in the yeare ſucceeding: for which cauſes the Scythians and Armenians very highly honoured him, thinking him to pertake of the divine na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and ſupernall knowledge, and therefore called him <hi>Olybama</hi> &amp; <hi>Arſa,</hi> which is as much as to ſay, the Heaven, and the Sunne: and they afterward alſo built and named many great citties in his name and of his wife <hi>Titea,</hi> ſo much were they honoured for their vertues and godly converſation. He further taught thoſe people the uſe of agriculture and tillage of the ground, and alſo the finding out of the uſe of the grape, and the manner to plant vines and other neceſſaries for their more eaſie living, wherup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hee was entearmed alſo <hi>Ianus,</hi> which in the Scythian tongue, ſignifies the giver of wine. But as he was the firſt that found out the uſe thereof, ſo was hee the firſt that felt the power and vertue of it, who not being able to endure the fume and mightie ſtrength of the operation thereof, in a great feaſt wherto he had envited many of his friends, fell extreamely drunke, and ſo overcome therewith, as he lay ſenceleſly ſleeping in unſeemely manner amid theſe his gueſts and friends ſo envited: ſuch was the furie of
<pb facs="tcp:9480:6"/>
that new-found drinke.</p>
            <p>Among all the ſonnes of <hi>Noe, Cham</hi> was the leaſt in his fathers favor, who alſo by reaſon of his Magicke art (wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he had great knowledge) was called <hi>Zoroaſt,</hi> who wholly gave himſelfe over unto all incivilitie and rude behaviors, following the abhominations and vices of thoſe horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble giants before the floud: he, as hating his owne father, for that he ſaw himſelfe leaſt beloved of him, as he ſaw him thus lying drunke (uſing ſome charmes of enchantment) tooke now the time of revenge, and by his Magick ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witched his father in thoſe places of generation, that hee diſabled him ever after to have the uſe of women, or to get more children: for theſe and other ſuch his deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble impieties, hee incurred the wrath and diſpleaſure of God, in moſt greevous manner, and was afterward bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed from his father; who afflicted him with no more pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment therein for ſuch his unnaturall deed ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted.</p>
            <p>Humane kind through the ſucceſſion of time, ſo much encreaſed and multiplied, that they were now enforced to ſeeke out ſome new habitations and places of abode: whereupon the good Patriarke <hi>Noe,</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Ianus,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to exhort the princes and cheefe of his familie, to put themſelves in ſearch for other countries and places of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidence, and there to build and erect villages and citties, for the ſocietie of humane converſation: and he thus al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotted unto them their regions and quarters, where to po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulat and inhabit. To <hi>Sem,</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Melchiſedech,</hi> he appointed Aſia the great, which in it ſelfe containes the halfe of the world: and hee had with him in his companie xxv. Rulers of his familie. Hee afterwards built the cittie
<pb facs="tcp:9480:7"/>
of Salem, now called Ieruſalem, and hee lived even untill the time of <hi>Abraham.</hi> Vnto <hi>Iaphet</hi> his brother was allotted Europe, and he had with him foureteene rulers of his ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration: and unto theſe two, <hi>Noe</hi> bequeathd his bleſſing moſt amply, according as the ſcripture maketh mention: As for <hi>Cham,</hi> although he was out of grace with his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, yet had hee his inheritage alſo allowed unto him, which was the other third part of the world, as hereafter ſhall be farther ſpoken of.</p>
            <p>Frier <hi>Iohn Annius</hi> of Viterbe, the expoſitor of our author <hi>Beroſus,</hi> doth recite, that <hi>Philo</hi> the Iew (another very ancient author) doth write, That in the hundred year after the deluge, <hi>Noe</hi> to ſhew and inſtruct his children in Coſmographie, went upon the mountaines which over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>looke the Ponticke ſea (part of which is now called Mare Mediterraneum) and there ſhewed unto his ſonne <hi>Sem</hi> all the Aſiaticke ſeas, from the floud Tanais in Tartaria un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the river Nilus in Aegypt: unto <hi>Cham</hi> he ſhewed all the rivers iſſuing from the ſeas of Affrica, and from thence through Aegypt to the ſtreights of Gybraltar: and to <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet</hi> all the rivers and flouds of Europe, paſſing from thoſe ſtreights, through Spaine, Fraunce, and Italie, and thoſe countries round about; into which countrey of Italie <hi>Noe</hi> alſo afterward arrived, and left behind him certaine of his people in that part of the country where Rome was long after built, which was eight hundred yeares after the floud: from thence he paſſed unto the coaſts of Greece, and entred into the ſtraights leading to Conſtantinople, by the ſea called Mare Major, and ſo againe to the flouds of Tanais in Tartaria, from whence he firſt ſet forth. And it is to bee noted, That as hee paſſed through all thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:9480:7"/>
countries, he alwaies left people behind him to inhabit and encreaſe in thoſe countries, deſtributing unto every number certaine quarters to remaine in: and after this time, in ſhort ſpace many countries were againe reinha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited and peopled afreſh, which ſince the floud were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolat, and lay naked and depopulat.</p>
            <p>About the one and twentieth yeare of this his returne from the above written voyage, <hi>Noe</hi> began to divide king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, &amp; alſo to erect monarchies in the world: of which the firſt was the monarchie of Babylon, over the which, <hi>Nembroth</hi> the Giant, the ſonne of his nephew <hi>Cus,</hi> who was the ſonne of <hi>Cham,</hi> was firſt of all eſtabliſhed, in the hundred and one and thirtieth year after the inundation; and hee was called the firſt <hi>Saturne</hi> or king over the Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonians and Aſſyrians, who afterward in a faire Campania called Sennaar, laid the foundation, and erected the great tower and citie of Babell, which he had cauſed to be built even to the height of the higheſt mountaines, but after by the confuſion of languages it was given over and left unfiniſhed. <hi>Nembroth</hi> after this lived in peace and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quilitie 56 yeares.</p>
            <p>Not many years after the ſetting up of the monarchie of Babylon, <hi>Noe</hi> divided foure particular kingdomes in Europe, <hi>viz.</hi> the kingdome of Italie, Spain, Fraunce, and of Almaigne: for in Italie raigned <hi>Comerus Gallus,</hi> the eldeſt ſonne of <hi>Iaphet:</hi> in Spaine ruled <hi>Tuball</hi> (called alſo <hi>Iuball</hi>) the fifteenth ſonne of <hi>Iaphet:</hi> in Fraunce <hi>Samothes</hi> (ſurnamed <hi>Dis) Iaphets</hi> fourth ſonne: and over Almaign, (now called Germanie) governed the Giant <hi>Tuyſcon,</hi> one of the ſonnes of <hi>Noe.</hi> And ſo likewiſe in many other places of the world were ſeverall governements and
<pb facs="tcp:9480:8"/>
kingdomes then erected, which now to recite, were tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and impertinent to our purpoſe; &amp; every one of them a long time kept and were contented with their quarters ſo allotted unto them, and impoſed lawes and edicts unto their people, and they called the countrey after their own name, as alſo many mountaines, rivers, and townes were ſo entearmed, to the end, that all ſucceeding poſteritie might know by what meanes and by whome ſuch citties and other monuments receaved their firſt ground and foundation.</p>
            <p>After theſe kingdomes and governements erected, and the earth now againe well peopled, <hi>Noe</hi> now underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth his ſecond voiage into Europe, leaving <hi>Sabatius Saga</hi> his nephew, and brother to <hi>Nembroth</hi> king of Babylon, to governe and commaund over the countrey of Arme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia, from whence hee now departeth with purpoſe to viſit his children, and to know of their eſtates. And this <hi>Saba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius Saga</hi> (called alſo <hi>Saturne</hi>) had all the countrey even unto the land of Bactria, lying towards India (at this day called Tartaria) under his rule and authoritie. Theſe things at home thus eſtabliſhed, <hi>Noe</hi> (ſurnamed <hi>Ianus</hi>) with his wife <hi>Titea,</hi> and many multitudes of people be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, began his voyage (which was eight ſcore and nine yeares after the floud, and in the eight and thirtieth yeare of the raigne of <hi>Nembroth</hi>) towards Hyrcania, which he then peopled, and called them after his owne name Ianij. From thence he came to Meſopotamia, where alſo he left behind him many people to inhabit: and from thence he attained the countrey called Arabia Foelix, where he ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted two citties, the one called Noa, the other Ianinea, furniſhing them with inhabitants: after, hee paſſed from
<pb facs="tcp:9480:8"/>
thence, and came into Affrica, which part of the world hee firſt aſſigned unto the governement and ſoveraigne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of his ſecond ſonne <hi>Cham,</hi> but at that time there ruled <hi>Triton</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Saba,</hi> which was the ſon of <hi>Cus,</hi> the eldeſt ſonne of the ſame <hi>Cham.</hi> This <hi>Triton</hi> receaved <hi>Noe</hi> and his companie with great joy and gladneſſe of hart, and he ſtaied there ſome halfe a year, in which time <hi>Triton</hi> died, and left his ſonne <hi>Hammon</hi> inheritour to the kingdome of Affrica, otherwiſe called Lybia. After this, <hi>Noe</hi> paſſed forward, and at the length arrived in Spaine, which was two hundred fiftie nine yeares after the floud, and in the tenth yeare of the raigne of <hi>Ninus</hi> the third king of Babylon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iuball</hi> or <hi>Tuball,</hi> the fift ſon of <hi>Iaphet,</hi> and the firſt king of Spaine (as all hyſtories do affirme) received his grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father <hi>Noe Ianus,</hi> and his grandmother <hi>Tytea,</hi> with hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable entertainement and all gladſome willingneſſe: who alſo were exceeding joyfull to ſee the proſperous eſtate of their nephew <hi>Iuball,</hi> for ſo much as they found, that hee governed his people with great juſtice, policie, and good lawes, as <hi>Beroſus</hi> in a certaine place alleadgeth, ſaying: <hi>Anno Nini quarto Tuyſcon gigas Sarmatas, legibus format apud Rhenum: Idipſum agit Iubal apud Celtiberos (hoc eſt Hiſpanos) &amp; Samothes apud Celtas. Noe</hi> therefore to helpe his nephew for the better peopling of his countrey, foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded there two great citties, calling the one Noela and the other Noegla, in remembrance and honour of thoſe his two faire daughters, ſo called, beeing the wives of <hi>Iaphet</hi> and <hi>Cham:</hi> &amp; after this, departed for Italie to his nephew or grand child <hi>Comerus Gallus,</hi> the firſt ſonne of <hi>Iaphet,</hi> whom before he had appointed to bee king of that coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey.
<pb facs="tcp:9480:9"/>
In this voyage, and in his remaine in Spaine, were ſpent nine yeares. Now it is not written, whether he went this journey into Italie by land or ſea, notwithſtanding it is very likely, and agreeth with good probabilitie, that in this his voyage he would not paſſe by without viſiting the wiſe prince, his nephew <hi>Samothes,</hi> the brother of <hi>Iuball</hi> king of Spaine, who was by his appointment created the firſt king of Fraunce, as is before touched, and hee had raigned about this time ſixe ſcore yeares, and lived after this in peace and tranquillitie five and thirtie yeares and upward.</p>
            <p>The ſecond time of the comming of <hi>Ianus</hi> thus into Italie, was in the time of his age eight hundred and three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore yeares (and now eight ſcore ſince his laſt departure from thence) where thinking to find <hi>Comerus Gallus,</hi> hee now underſtood that he was dead, and that his ſon <hi>Cham,</hi> (contrarie to the appointment of <hi>Noe</hi>) not contented with the ſoveraigne domination of Affrica, had there wrongfully uſurped the ſiegnorie of Italie, and had now commaunded over that countrey five and twentie yeares or therabouts: and which was worſe, as all the other kings in Europe had inſtructed and governed their people in civilitie, manners, and education, hee contrarie to ſuch their good examples, had moſt abhominably corrupted the youth of Italie with all manner of impieties, vices, and odious ſinnes, which he with the helpe of thoſe peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple (called Aborigines, which he brought along with him to people the countrey) made them to embrace, entertain and live in. <hi>Noe</hi> upon the knowledge of this, waxt mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellous heavie and diſcontent, as ſorrowing for the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlineſſe of his owne ſonne, and ſuffered him thus for
<pb facs="tcp:9480:9"/>
the ſpace of three years to continue therin, hoping dayly to ſee ſome amendment or other in him: but finding him to perſever therin, and rather to encreaſe in it than other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, hee baniſht him, with a certaine number of people with him, from out the confines of Italie; from whence departed, hee arrived in the Iſland of Sicilia, where hee with his companie long after lived.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ianus</hi> then taking upon himſelfe the kingdome of Italy, which was now two hundred threeſcore and twelve yeares after the floud, he began like a carefull governour to root out and ſeperate the infectious ſheepe out of the whole flocke, leaſt with their impurities all ſhould be corrupted, and ſo hee choſe out a certaine number of people which were tainted with the vices of their commaunder that laſt ruled (and which people were called Aborigenes) &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them to depart out of the country, over the river Tybre, firſt called Ianiculum: which thing they performed and demaunded for their queene and governeſſe <hi>Crana, Noes</hi> daughter, which hee alſo graunted them: and he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed a kingdome and government for them, and they were as is alreadie ſaid, called Aborigines, &amp; thoſe which were left in Italie, were called Ianigines, after his owne name. He had not long rained here, but he cauſed to bee built on this ſide of the river Tybre, towards Tuſcania, a marvellous great cittie on the top of a high mountaine, which he then called Ianiculum, &amp; after that Vaticanum, and ſince the towne of S. <hi>Peter</hi> of Rome, and it was ſeated on the ſame place, which at this day S. <hi>Peters</hi> church ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth upon, as alſo the Popes pallace, called at this day in Italian, <hi>Belvedere,</hi> which is as much as, The faire ſight. Round about thoſe countries to the river Arnus, which
<pb facs="tcp:9480:10"/>
paſſeth through Florence, to the bounds of Sardinia, did <hi>Noe</hi> cauſe to bee inhabited and made populous in thoſe daies: wherein alſo he built and erected many moſt beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull cities, which he called Aryn Ianas, <hi>id est, ex Iano ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altatas:</hi> and hee began then alſo to write and ſet downe lawes and inſtitutions for the civile adminiſtration of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and government of Commonweales, which he firſt preſcribed in the citie of Vetulonia, called ſince Viterbe: and inſtructed the people alſo in the ſciences of Phyſicke, Aſtronomie, and Divinitie, and in the ceremonious rites and cuſtomes belonging to holy ſacrifices; and of theſe alſo he made many and ſeverall bookes.</p>
            <p>It hath beene mentioned before, how that upon <hi>Noes</hi> laſt departure out of Armenia, hee conſtituted and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed his nephew <hi>Sabatius Saga,</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Saturne,</hi> to rule as King and Patriarke over that countrey; wherein he afterward raigned peaceably, even untill the time of the raigne of <hi>Iupiter Belus,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Nembroth,</hi> the ſecond king of Babilon: who yeelding unto his diſordinat deſires, and coveting to command as ſole Monarch of the whole world, was the firſt violater &amp; infringer of the ordinances appointed in thoſe daies, and by whoſe means the golden age afterward loſt ſuch her title, and never ſince was called ſo: for before ſuch his over haughtie humors, all things were peaceable, common, &amp; free. This <hi>Iupiter</hi> endevored by all deviſes poſſible to overturne the greatneſſe of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batius Saga,</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Saturne,</hi> and commanded alſo his ſonne <hi>Ninus</hi> to undertake all meanes how to bring him and his family to death and deſtruction: which thing they jointly effectuated ſo far, as hardly eſcaped hee the ſnares and ſubtilties laid to entrap him. <hi>Saturne</hi> therefore ſeeing
<pb facs="tcp:9480:10"/>
himſelfe in thoſe daungers and caſualties, to be deprived of all dignitie and commaund, for ſuccour and refuge fled unto his grandfather <hi>Noe,</hi> there hoping to bee protected, ſafe guarded, and defended, which thing alſo <hi>Virgil</hi> thus remembreth: <hi>Primus ab ethereo venit Saturnus Olimpo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Virgil.</hi> Whereupon Poets feign, that <hi>Saturne</hi> was baniſht heaven by <hi>Iupiter.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>arma Iovis fugiens &amp; regnis exul ademptis. Noe,</hi> according to the expectation of <hi>Saturn,</hi> friendly entertained him, &amp; gave him many gracious ſignes of his welcome &amp; wiſhed arrivall: and for to honour him the more, and to ſhew the effects of his friendſhip and good will towards him, crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him the Commaunder, King, and Patriarke of the Aborigenes, whom lately wee ſpecified: and there cauſed him alſo to build a citie, which hee called after his owne name, Saturnia, hard by that of <hi>Ianus,</hi> called Ianiculum; in which very place at this day one part of Rome, which lieth on the other ſide of the river Tybre, ſtandeth, and is erected; as <hi>Virgil</hi> alſo in his Eneidos mentioneth,<note place="margin">Virgil.</note> where he bringeth in <hi>Aeneas</hi> ſpeaking to <hi>Evander,</hi> ſaying: <hi>Haec duo preterea diſiectis opida muris, Reliquias veterum vides monumenta virorum, Ianiculum huic, fuerat, illi Saturnia nomen. Ianus</hi> then and <hi>Saturne</hi> thus raigning together, <hi>Titea</hi> the great, <hi>Noes</hi> wife, began in thoſe times firſt to ſet up the order of Nuns, and ceremonies of Veſtall virgins, inventing then the ſetting up of lights and lampes in the churches and temples dedicated to the profeſſion of vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginitie and chaſtitie, which cuſtome was in thoſe daies very reverently regarded, and endured in great honor and reputation, even unto the time of the Romanes. <hi>Saturne</hi> likewiſe very painefully inſtructed the people in tillage, and in the nature of ſoiles, wherein he had great skill and knowledge, as alſo in the ceremonies of religion: and not
<pb facs="tcp:9480:11"/>
long after (having inſtituted his ſonne <hi>Sabus</hi> to bee the ſucceſſor to the kingdome of the Sabines and Aborige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes) he died, in the three hundred and fortie fourth yeare after the inundation of the world. In the very ſame yeare alſo, <hi>Noe Ianus</hi> finding &amp; perceiving his end to approch, and that now his luſtineſſe and vigour of ſpirits began to ſhrinke and decreaſe, created one of his ſonnes, called <hi>Cranus,</hi> the King and Patriarke over the Ianigenes (which are now called Tuſcanes) and the ſixt yeare after departed this life, and gave up to his maker, his noble and heroicke ſpirit: which was after he had raigned in Italie foureſcore and two yeares, and after the floud three hundred fortie ſix yeares, before the foundation of Troy foure hundred and foureſcore, and before the incarnation of Chriſt, one thouſand nine hundred threeſcore and ſeven yeares, and in the age of the ſame <hi>Noe,</hi> nine hundred and fiftie.</p>
            <p>The death of this good King and Patriarke poſſeſſed almoſt all the people in the world with great ſorrow and lamentation, and eſpecially the Armenians and Italians, who in moſt honorable manner celebrated his obſequies with ſuch their then uſed rites and ceremonies, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward dedicated and attributed unto him divine honours and godlike adoration, building and conſecrating tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and holy aultars unto him, calling him by divers and ſeverall names and titles, as the Sun, the Heaven, the Seed of the world, the Father of the gods, the Soul of the world, the God of peace, the giver of juſtice and holineſſe, the expulſer of things hurtfull: alſo their children and ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours called him <hi>Ianus, Geminus, Quadriſons, Enoirius, Ogyges, Vertumnus, Vadymon, Protheus, Multiſors, Dieſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> and <hi>Iupiter:</hi> and they invented all manner of honours
<pb facs="tcp:9480:11"/>
and ſtraunge worſhips to reverence and adore him: they alſo ſhaped foorth his picture into diverſe formes and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhions: ſometimes ſetting him foorth with two faces, to ſignifie thereby his wiſdome upon every matter and every occaſion: ſometimes alſo with foure faces, to denotate therby that he was the god of the yeare for that he had ſo devided it into four ſeveral parts, being the Spring, Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, Autumn, and Winter,<note place="margin">Macrobius.</note> as <hi>Macrobius</hi> in his Saturnals alſo remembreth, ſaying: <hi>Ianus apud nos in quatuor partes ſpectat, ut demonstrateius ſimulachrum èphaleris advectu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> Afterwards, the Phenicians pourtraied him foorth in the forme of a Dragon, biting her taile, to ſhew thereby the roundneſſe, and the beginning and ending of the yeare. In honour of him alſo at this day the firſt moneth of the yeare is called after his owne name Ianuarius,<note place="margin">Servius.</note> as <hi>Servius</hi> in his Aeneidos affirmeth. The ancients likewiſe have ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped him forth with two keyes in his hand, to ſhew thereby that he was the invent or of gates and dores, as alſo of the locking of them and making them faſt, to the end, that the holy temples and ſacred places ſhould not bee polluted with the impious abuſe of theeves and uncivile perſons, and to avoid adulteries and other ſuch like ſinnes then raigning; and of his name ſince have all dores and gates been called Ianuae. In many other ſorts and formes have the auncients defigured the image of this <hi>Noe Ianus,</hi> as <hi>Propertius</hi> and many others have written, who in the fourth booke of his Elegies, thus ſpeaketh:
<q>
                  <l>Quid mirare meas tot in uno corpore formas?</l>
                  <l>Accipe Vertumni ſigna paterna dei</l>
                  <l>Tuſcus ego Tuſcis orior, &amp;c.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:9480:12"/>And undoubtedly, there hath not beene read of any that lived ſo uprightly and juſtly as this Patriarke <hi>Noe,</hi> neither that ever any had ſuch honours, reverence, and godlike adoration done unto him, both in his life time, and after his death, who alſo was among thoſe people in thoſe daies called God: neither is it to bee wondered, that in thoſe elder times there were ſo many gods held &amp; wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped among the auncients, for ſo much as it is to bee underſtood, That in thoſe daies all thoſe princes, rulers, and governors that had lived vertuouſly, juſtly, and godly, and had commaunded their people with mildneſſe, equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and uprightneſſe, were entearmed gods, and that alſo without performing any idolatrous adoration or reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence unto them, as <hi>Metaſthenes,</hi> an auncient author and hyſtorian of Perſia affirmeth, where hee thus ſaith: <hi>Ante Nynum ducentis &amp; quadragintà novem annis regnatum fuit ſub tribus dijs regibus, quorum qui primus univerſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peravit orbi, fuit Ogyges, qui prefuit inundationi terraru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp;c. Cathon</hi> alſo, another very auncient writer, thus ſpeaketh: <hi>Italia complura a dijs &amp; ducibus ſortita fuit nomina, à Iano Ianicula quem quidem Enotrium dictum exiſtimant, quia invenit uvum &amp; far.</hi> And for theſe and ſuch like reaſons, <hi>Moyſes</hi> and other godly Patriarkes were called gods, not that they were ſo in eſſence, but onely in participation, as in the ſeventh chapter of Exodus it is written: <hi>Ego te dedi deum Pharaoni:</hi> and in the the three and twenty chapter, <hi>Dijs non detrahes, &amp; principem populi tui ne maledicas.</hi> Further alſo the Prophet <hi>David</hi> thus ſayth: <hi>Principes po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulorum congregati ſunt, cum deo Abraham, quoniam dij fortes terrae vehementer elevati ſunt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe things are thus ſo amply and at large expoſed,
<pb facs="tcp:9480:12"/>
to the end, that the reader of this Treatiſe ſhould not ſo much marvell or wonder when mention is made in this booke of gods and goddeſſes, which in thoſe daies were ſo much obſerved and reverenced.<note place="margin">Ovid.</note> 
               <hi>Ovid</hi> rehearſing the words of this <hi>Noe Ianus,</hi> and ſhewing that in his death the golden age ceaſed, thus ſayth: <q>
                  <l>Tunc ego regnabam patiens cum terra deorum</l>
                  <l>Eſſet, &amp; humanis numina mixta locis</l>
                  <l>Nondum iuſtitiam, facinus mortale fugarat,</l>
                  <l>Vltima de ſuperis illa reliquit humum,</l>
                  <l>Proque meta populum, ſive vt pudor ille regebat,</l>
                  <l>Nullus erat iuſtis reddere iura labor</l>
                  <l>Nil mihi cum bello, poſtes pacem que tuebar, &amp;c.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And as <hi>Noe</hi> was among theſe auncients thus honored and adored, and temples and altars conſecrated unto him: ſo alſo was <hi>Titea</hi> his wife held in great reverence, worſhip, and holy eſteeme, who was called alſo <hi>Veſta, Aretia, Terra, Regina ſacrorum, magna Cybeles, Materque deorum, atque Vestalium Princeps, ſive Abbatiſsa,</hi> as <hi>Beroſus</hi> and other writers affirme. Having thus touched the death of this good Patriarke <hi>Noe,</hi> it ſhall not bee now impertinent ſomething to remember and ſpeake of the wicked and abhominable life of his degenerate ſonne <hi>Cham,</hi> which although of it ſelfe it be worthleſſe of any recapitulation or recitall, yet to deſcend to the lineall genealogie of the Lybian <hi>Hercules</hi> the Great, it cannot bee well omitted: from which <hi>Hercules, Dardanus</hi> the firſt founder and erecter of Troy, deſcended and came.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:9480:13"/>It hath been alreadie ſpecified, how <hi>Noe</hi> deviding the univerſall earth unto his children, and how <hi>Cham</hi> aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in all vices and deteſtable courſes, notwithſtanding was not deprived of his portion, but had his right of inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance juſtly allotted unto him, which was the third part of the world, and particularly Affrica to the hether part of Aegypt; for which countries he was commaunded by his father to depart, with his wife <hi>Noegla,</hi> and five and thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie rulers (which is as much to ſay, as the cheefes of fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie of his bloud and houſe) as alſo with all their children and iſſue: which was accordingly performed, and preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he eſtabliſhed himſelfe as king and <hi>Saturne</hi> of Aegypt, where he erected and built a citie called Chem-Myn: and among them alſo, he himſelfe was called <hi>Pan,</hi> and <hi>Silva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> which people likewiſe (ſo engendred and iſſued of that familie) to honour and worſhip him the more, and to ſhew their love unto him, lived in all impious and ungra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious manner, perpetrating moſt odious and ſoule-dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning villanies, affirming publickly, That men ought law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to have the companie of their owne mothers, ſiſters, and daughters, in all luſts and concupiſcence of the fleſh; and other many moſt inhumane and ſhamefull acts, not to be recited. And to ſhew that they gloried and boſted in the wickedneſſe of ſuch their king and ruler, they entear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med him by the name of <hi>Cham Eſenuus,</hi> which ſignifieth their infamous god <hi>Pan.</hi> And thus he ruled in Egipt long time, even unto the ſix and fiftith yeare of the raigne of <hi>Iupiter Belus,</hi> the ſecond king of Babylon: in the which yeare he began to travell, and came into Italie (which was then called Kytim) to his brother <hi>Comerus Gallus,</hi> the firſt king of that countrey; after whoſe death, <hi>Cham</hi> preſently
<pb facs="tcp:9480:13"/>
uſurped and undertooke that mightie governement: who in ſtead of vertuous inſtructions and godly laws, in which all other princes round about him, his kinſmen (com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunding Germanie, Spaine, and France) had inſtructed and taught their people, cleane contrarie infected the youth of Italie with all manner of impieties, incivilitie, and corruptible vices: perſuading them (beeing of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves well addicted) to uſurie, robberie, murder, poyſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, and the ſtudie of the Magicke art, who by reaſon of his owne great skill therein, was ſurnamed <hi>Zoroaſtes,</hi> and was the firſt inventor and practiſer of that vild and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abolicall learning, of the uſe of which hee compoſed and writ many bookes, and hee was called generally through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the world, <hi>Cam Eſenuus, id eſt, Cam infamis, &amp; impudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus, propagator.</hi> Some have thought, That the Turke for thoſe and ſuch like cauſes, is called in his letters patents, <hi>le grand Cam de Tartaria.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is written, That <hi>Cham</hi> had one ſiſter which was called Rhea, maried to <hi>Hammon</hi> king of Lybia, who alſo was enamoured of one other faire woman, called <hi>Almanthea,</hi> and had of her by adulterous meanes, a ſon, whoſe name afterwards was <hi>Dionyſius;</hi> which child was ſecretly broght up and nouriſhed in a certaine citie of Arabia, called Ny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa: notwithſtanding, the matter was not ſo cloſely &amp; cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly handled, but his wife <hi>Rhea</hi> had privie advertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments thereof. Whereupon in deſpight and jealous diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content, ſhe forſooke her husband, and went home to her brother <hi>Cham</hi> (then abiding in the Iſland of Sicilia) who preſently maried and eſpouſed her, and (as ſome writers hold) his wife <hi>Noegla</hi> being alive: but of this other he after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards got many children, as <hi>Cus</hi> the father of <hi>Nembroth,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:9480:14"/>
the firſt king of Babylon, <hi>Typhon</hi> the gyant, and alſo many others.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cham</hi> and his owne ſiſter <hi>Rhea</hi> thus maried together, they conſulted and adviſed to be revenged of king <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> of Lybia, and to that effect raiſed a great armie of men, and with the aſſiſtance and helpe of their brothers (the ſixteene gyants) they ſet forwards from Sycilia, and in the end arrived within the territories and confines of Lybia, where they gave king <hi>Hammon</hi> battell, and in the field overthrew and vanquiſht him, ſo that he was glad to flie into the Iſle of Crete (now called Candia:) not long after this, <hi>Rhea</hi> had a ſonne of her husband <hi>Cham,</hi> called <hi>Oſyris,</hi> afterwards ſurnamed <hi>Iupiter Iuſtus,</hi> who prooved a moſt noble and gallant prince, far differing from the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked humors and diſpoſitions of his father.</p>
            <p>After this, about the three and fortieth yeare of the raigne of <hi>Nynus</hi> king of Babylon, <hi>Dionyſius</hi> the ſonne of king <hi>Hammon</hi> and of the faire <hi>Almanthea,</hi> now beeing come to age and of mans eſtate, began now to think up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the wrong offered unto his father by <hi>Cham</hi> &amp; <hi>Rhea,</hi> in uſurping the commaund of Lybia, and determined ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly to bee revenged upon them, which alſo hee af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards performed, and expulſt them againe out of the countrey, inveſting himſelfe in the regaltie thereof. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, he uſed <hi>Oſyris</hi> (the yong ſonne of <hi>Cham</hi> and <hi>Rhea</hi>) with great clemencie and mercie, and receaved him as his adopted child, and in remembrance of his father called him alſo <hi>Hammon</hi> and <hi>Iupiter:</hi> and brought him up very carefully in the ſtudie of letters and other neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie gifts: over whom he appointed as ſchoolmaiſter and tutor, a learned man called <hi>Olympus,</hi> of whom afterwards
<pb facs="tcp:9480:14"/>
               <hi>Oſyris</hi> took his name, and was ſurnamed <hi>Olympicus.</hi> After that <hi>Cham</hi> and his wife and ſiſter <hi>Rhea</hi> were thus diſcomfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and overthrowne by <hi>Dionyſius</hi> the new king of Lybia, and now retired with ſuch diſgrace into the furthermoſt and obſcureſt corners of Aegypt; <hi>Rhea</hi> was preſently upon this, delivered of a daughter called <hi>Iuno,</hi> which was alſo called <hi>Iſis</hi> the Great: and this was in the firſt yeare of the raigne of <hi>Semyramis,</hi> which was three hundred and two yeares after the floud: and this <hi>Iſis</hi> was accounted for the faireſt, as alſo the beſt diſpoſed ladie of the world. But her unfortunat &amp; wicked father <hi>Cham,</hi> now remaining in Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt (as hath beene alreadie ſpecified) was not contented with ſuch his habitation there, but ſeeking further (as over ambitiouſly enclined) arrived in the countrey of Bactria, not far from Perſia, where he ſo wrought and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed with his diabolicall skill of Negromancie, that he ſubjugated and brought under all thoſe people therea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouts, inſomuch as hee there raigned in great puiſſance, pride, and mightineſſe: and yet not with this ſatisfied, ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thereth great troupes and armies of men, and invadeth the Aſſyrians, againſt whome marcheth their king called <hi>Nynus</hi> the young, the ſonne of the before mentioned <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myramis,</hi> whoſe fortune was ſuch, as hee victoriouſly tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphed over his enemy <hi>Cham,</hi> ſuppreſſing his glory, rule, and haughtineſſe, he himſelfe being in that battell ſlaine, and all the armie ſhamefully diſcomfited.</p>
            <p>Many writers have affirmed, That this <hi>Cham</hi> was a man of ſingular ingenuitie and ſharpe capacitie, and that hee firſt found out the ſeven liberall Sciences, and had wrote many bookes of great worth, among which, his cheefeſt were of Negromancie, of which, moſt part of them were
<pb facs="tcp:9480:15"/>
burned by the beforeſaid <hi>Nynus.</hi> Some alſo ſay, That hee onely in the world came out of his mothers womb laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and with a ſmiling countenance, which is an uncouth thing, and (as moſt hold) prognoſticating no good. Vnto this <hi>Cham, Tiphon</hi> the Gyant (his eldeſt ſonne by <hi>Noegla</hi>) was heire, and alſo ſucceeded him in humors and malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous diſpoſitions, who was brought up in Aegypt, &amp; there continued. And now alſo it ſhall bee fit to revert our hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorie unto the two yongeſt children of <hi>Cham Zoroaſtes,</hi> which excelled in all good parts and vertuous inclination as their father abounded in the contrary, &amp; that was that <hi>Oſyris</hi> before ſpoken of (the adopted ſonne of <hi>Dionyſius,</hi> king of Lybia) and <hi>Iſis</hi> his ſiſter, the faireſt &amp; beſt accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſht damoſell in the world, whom afterward he tooke to wife and maried, with whome hee had alſo the kingdome and principalitie of Aegypt. Theſe two now newly eſpou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, he being of threeſcore yeares of age, and ſhee about fiftie (and yet our author <hi>Beroſus</hi> tearms them very youth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full) began to applie themſelves to the ſtudie of the nature of hearbes, and to the finding out of planting, tilling, and ſowing of corne, which afterwards they inſtructed their people in, and ſhewed the uſe to their neighbors dwelling in Paleſtina, of which ruled king and governour <hi>Sem,</hi> ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named <hi>Melchiſedech,</hi> who was the firſt that ever offered bread and wine unto God. From thence <hi>Oſyris</hi> paſſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Aegypt, and there alſo very painefully ſhewed them the manner of tilling and agriculture, as likewiſe the Poet <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bullus</hi> ſpeaketh of,<note place="margin">Tibullus.</note> ſaying:
<q>
                  <l>Primus aratra manu ſolerti fecit Oſyris,</l>
                  <l>Et tenerum ferro ſollicitavit humum.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:9480:15"/>Afterward he travelled into many other countries, alwaies learning them (then living by acornes, nuts, and water) in the knowledge of ſuch his new invention; and by theſe gentle and mild courſes hee gained the love of all people, and by that meanes almoſt poſſeſt himſelfe of all the world, with the regalities and principalities there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of (the Empire of Babylon onely excepted) whoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts, victories, prevailements, and powers, we wil ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more amplie hereafter remember, following as wel our owne authour <hi>Beroſus,</hi> as alſo <hi>Diodorus Siculus,</hi> the learned <hi>Catasthenes,</hi> and many other authenticke authors herein in their bookes and writings of matters of elder times, and ſubiects of antiquity <hi>Oſyris</hi> therfore (ſurnamed <hi>Iupiter Iuſtus</hi>) having by his wife and ſiſter <hi>Iſis</hi> (otherwiſe called <hi>Iuno</hi>) and alſo of many other ladies, which here ſhal bee needleſſe to recite) many children, as <hi>Hercules</hi> the great, <hi>Anubis, Macedon, Lidus, Meon, Neptune, Oros,</hi> and alſo many others, hee aſſembleth a mightie armie of all ſorts of people, both puiſſant and ſubtill, and leaving the governement of the kingdome of Aegypt to the queene <hi>Iſis,</hi> carying along with him ſome of his aforeſaid chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, he taketh a long and weariſome journy. The cheefe place of commaund in all his armie, hee appointed unto his eldeſt ſon <hi>Hercules</hi> of Lybia, who upon his eſcutchion and armes, bare depainted the ſhape of a crowned Lion rampant, holding in his forefeet a mightie hatchet. His two other brothers, <hi>Anubis</hi> and <hi>Macedon,</hi> caried defigured on their ſhields, the one a Dog, the other a Wolfe; accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſignification of their names. The armes of the Emperour <hi>Oſyris</hi> was a royall ſcepter, and under that, the forme of an eye: as who ſearcheth the monuments of
<pb facs="tcp:9480:16"/>
antiquitie, may there find it out: by which is perceived how auncient an uſage the giving of armes is, and how to bee reſpected. And in thoſe times all good and juſt princes were called gods, as <hi>Pan, Apollo, Iupiter,</hi> and infinit others, with their goddeſſes, muſes, and nymphs.</p>
            <p>This mightie, powerfull, and gallant armie thus gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red together, the Emperour <hi>Oſyris</hi> proceedeth in his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended voyage, and therein compaſſeth round the whole univerſall earth: his firſt reſiſtance was upon his entering into Affrica, where was oppoſed againſt him the Gyant <hi>Antheus,</hi> but him he preſently overthrew. After that, hee quietly paſſed into India and Aethyopia, where hee did great good in inſtructing the poore ignorant people in the true knowledge of neceſſarie nutriment and victuals, telling them the manner how to governe and command with policie, juſtice, and equitie. Here alſo hee ſubdued many moſt ougly and fierce Gyants, full of crueltie and bloud, who generally with their greatneſſe had tyrannized over all thoſe countries of Aſia. He ſlew the tyrant <hi>Buſiris</hi> of Phoenicia, which uſed to ſacrifice men and women un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the gods. After this, hee arrived in Phrygia, and there alſo ſubjugated the Gyant <hi>Typhon,</hi> in whoſe commaund and place he eſtabliſhed one of his owne ſonnes, ruling there, beeing the place where Troy afterward was ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted. From thence hee came by long paſſages, into this part of the world, being Europe, through the ſtreights of the ſea called Helleſpont, ſince called the arm of S. <hi>George</hi> deviding Grecia from Turkie.</p>
            <p>At this time ruled in Thracia (which is that part of Greece where Conſtantinople is erected) a moſt horrible tyrant and inhumane Gyant called <hi>Lycurgus,</hi> who now
<pb facs="tcp:9480:16"/>
denied paſſage through his countrey unto <hi>Oſyris,</hi> and at the firſt fiercely reſiſted his approches, but in the end, in gallant fight, he ſlew him with his owne hands, and remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned victor and ſole commaunder of that countrey: which afterwards he reſigned to one of his owne followers called <hi>Maron,</hi> being a young and valiant prince. From thence he paſſed into another province called Emathia, in which alſo ruled many bloudie and cruell Gyants, all which hee cleane extirpated, deſtroyed, and ſubdued, ſetling the countrey in peaceable quietneſſe and ſecurity, over which he appointed to be commaunder, one of his own ſonnes before ſpoken of, called <hi>Macedon,</hi> who afterwards called that countrey after his owne name, Macedonia, and the people Macedonians, of whom deſcended and iſſued the everfamous conquerour, <hi>Alexander</hi> the great. Out of this countrey, the Emperour <hi>Oſyris</hi> preſently departed, and came into the Iſle of Crete (now called Candia) where he vanquiſhed the Gyant <hi>Milinus,</hi> a tyrannicall and ſoure governour, yet hee appointed his ſonne (in whome good hopes appeared of good governement) to be king of the ſaid Iſland. From theſe parts he returned again into Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia, and ſo to Scythia, now called Tartaria, where he found his eldeſt ſon, the great <hi>Hercules</hi> of Lybia, in proſperous eſtate: who at this inſtant was extreamely enamoured of a ladie called <hi>Araxa,</hi> by whom afterwards he begat a ſonne called <hi>Tuſcus,</hi> which long after was king of Italie, and of whome deſcended king <hi>Dardanus,</hi> the firſt founder and builder of Troy. From Tartaria, the mightie Emperour <hi>Oſyris</hi> (ſurnamed <hi>Iupiter Iuſtus</hi>) and his ſonne <hi>Hercules</hi> are now departed, and in ſhort ſpace arived in Hungarie, and ſo came into Almaign or Germanie, even unto the floud
<pb facs="tcp:9480:17"/>
of Duno, not farre from the famous river of Rhyne, where (finding the country ſomething populous) he made ſome ſtay and reſidence, painefully inſtructing them in the ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of corne and planting of vines: and builded alſo in this place diverſe villages and cities, of whom, hee beeing alſo ſurnamed <hi>Apis</hi>) the mighty houſe of the Counts of Haſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourgh in Germanie tooke her name; from which hath iſſued the noble and illuſtrious houſe of Auſtria, ſince in great power and greatneſſe exceedingly flouriſhing. He alſo there gave the names unto the cheefeſt hils &amp; moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines thereabouts, whereof at this day ſome are called Appenini. And from thence hee paſſed into Italie, which preſently ſhall be further ſhowne, and as that very ancient authour affirmeth,<note place="margin">Cathon.</note> whom wee call <hi>Cathon</hi> the auncient, ſaying:
<q>Aurea et as uſque ad Apina deorum Italiae ultimum, &amp;c.</q>
            </p>
            <p>In theſe times there reigned in Germanie a prince, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Gambrivius,</hi> the vij. king of the Germanes, deſcended from the houſe of <hi>Tuyſcon</hi> the Gyant, the firſt king of that countrey, and the ſonne of <hi>Noe.</hi> With this prince the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Oſyris</hi> made long reſidence, and was roially feaſted and entertained, as being indeed near in kinred and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanguinitie, who accordingly received him and his traine with great joy and gladneſſe. The countrey of Italie about this time was extreamly oppreſt with the tyrannie &amp; blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die faſhions of infinit numbers of Gyants that therabouts then lived, called <hi>Titans,</hi> inſomuch, as the people of the countrey, not able longer to tollerate and endure thoſe ſuch ſlaviſh impoſitions and unſufferable tyrannies, (hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb facs="tcp:9480:17"/>
of the fame and late arrivall of the Emperour <hi>Oſyris</hi> into Germanie) ſent their meſſengers or embaſſadours unto him, moſt humbly craving and deſiring his favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble aſſiſtance and protection againſt thoſe barbarous and uncivile oppreſſors, and that he would make a journy thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to deliver them from the miſerable ſervitude &amp; bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage that they then were forced to abide and live in. The Emperor <hi>Oſyris</hi> or <hi>Iupiter</hi> hearing and accepting of their diſtreſſed condition and caſe, willingly condeſcended to leave Germanie, and to undertake a voyage thither, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe and ſuppreſſe their wrongs, and the Gyants ſuper-arrogant pride, glory, and haughtineſſe: which, although they were of kinred and alliance unto him, yet in reſpect of their uncivile and tyrannicall uſances, he inſtantly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded to the redreſſement thereof: and in three ſeverall battels utterly overthrew, vanquiſht, and diſcomfited them, and thereupon tooke upon him the governement of the principalitie of Italie, which (long before) his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Cham</hi> and his grandfather <hi>Noe</hi> were alſo poſſeſſed of: and hee commaunded and ruled over the Italians for the ſpace of eleven yeares, where for the moſt part hee remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the citie of Viterbe, called alſo Vetulonia, and at the end of eleven yeares, in great triumph, joy, and glorie, inſtituted his nephew <hi>Leſtrigon</hi> the Gyant (the ſon of his ſon <hi>Neptune</hi>) king, commander, &amp; ruler over all the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey of Italie.</p>
            <p>But for ſo much as in this booke mention is made oftentimes of ſtrange and horrible Gyants, &amp; other rare and admirable things, the reader may perhaps remain in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credulous, and ſcarſe beleeve them to bee true, accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them wholly fabulous, and by invention faſhioned,
<pb facs="tcp:9480:18"/>
yet to alleadge ſome authoritie for the confirmation ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of (leaving out infinite other examples of infallible cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainetie) you only ſhall be referred to the holy ſcriptures, and alſo unto <hi>Ioſephus</hi> the Iewiſh writer, who amply hath handled the apologie therof: among the reſt, <hi>Nembroth, Golias,</hi> and others, are apparent, that they were Gyants, and of unuſuall ſtature, ſtrength, &amp; proportion of bodie. If the authoritie of <hi>Boccace</hi> may be accepted, he thus wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth of himſelfe: In my time (ſayth hee) there was found under the foot and hollow caverne of a mountaine, not far from the citie of Deprana, in the Iſle of Sicilia, the bodie of a marvellous, huge, and ſtrange proportioned Gyant, which ſeemed to hold in one of his hands a mightie long peece of wood like unto the bodie of a young tree, or the maſt of a ſhip, which ſo ſoone as it was touched, fell all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to aſhes and duſt, but it was all garniſht &amp; wrought about with lead, which remained ſound and firm, &amp; it was found to weigh five hundred pound weight: his bodie alſo being touched, conſumed, and became all pouder and aſhes, except certaine of his bones, and three of his teeth, which were alſo peized, and every tooth weighed fortie ounces. For the height and full ſtature of his bodie; it was conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctured by the people of that countrey, to be two hundred cubits long. And the ſame authour ſayth, That his teeth were afterwards hanged up in our ladies church of Depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, for a ſtraunge monument, and a thing of wonderfull admiration. In many other places are the bones of gyants that lived in thoſe daies, kept and preſerved for woonders and reliques of memorie, but yet not of ſo uncouth and almoſt incredible hugeneſſe: but leaving theſe matters to bee further ruminated by the ſcrupulous, I will returne
<pb facs="tcp:9480:18"/>
to our maine intendment proceeding, till I have further explaned the obſcuritie thereof.</p>
            <p>Theſe things above ſpoken of, being atchieved by <hi>Oſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris</hi> againſt thoſe Gyants and moleſters of civile converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he departed out of Italie with all his royall armie, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularly well prepared and in gallant equipage, accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with gods, heroes, demie gods, and martialiſts, that is, with all valiant, courageous, and wiſe princes, rulers, and captaines: and it is not written, whether in this his journey he paſſed through Gaule (now called Fraunce) or went that way by ſea, but hard by the continent hee coa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, in which then ruled one <hi>Lucus,</hi> king of that famous countrey: but howſoever he journeied, hee now is ſtrived in Spaine, where once againe hee renued mortall battels againſt the <hi>Tytans,</hi> which were mightie Gyants, and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſins to thoſe he before diſcomfited in Italie, theſe alſo hee now ſubdueth and quite raſeth out all their generation, leaving the governement of that countrey to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund of <hi>Gerion.</hi> And from thence he againe ſayled into Greece, and arived in the province of Peloponneſus, now called Morea: and hee there ſetled himſelfe, and ruled in the citie of Arges for the ſpace of five and thirtie yeares, as it is written by <hi>Euſebius</hi> in his booke of Time. After this he createth his ſonne <hi>Egialus,</hi> king of Achaia,<note place="margin">Euſebius.</note> and ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turneth againe into Aegypt, there to ſpend his latter daies with his wife and ſiſter <hi>Iſis,</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Iuno;</hi> who tooke ſuch his comming home in full joyous acceptance and glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome pleaſingneſſe. By this time all the world had beene filled with the report of <hi>Oſyris</hi> great fame and worthineſſe, unto whom were aſcribed and given many titles &amp; names of triumph, as <hi>Iupiter Iuſtus, Dux, Rex, Conſultor, Cuius
<pb facs="tcp:9480:19"/>
regnum perpetuum eſt, &amp; habitatio in Olympo:</hi> all which were cleane contrary to thoſe wherewith his father <hi>Cham</hi> was entituled.</p>
            <p>Being thus returned into his countrey of Aegypt, hee cauſed in many and ſeverall parts and corners thereof, to bee erected certaine columnes and high pillars, in which he commaunded to bee cut out and engraved for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation and memorie of his name and glory, theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing lines,<note place="margin">Diodorus Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culus.</note> as <hi>Diodorus Siculus</hi> repeateth them:
<q>Mihi pater Saturnus deorum olim iunior, ſum vero Oſyris rex, qui vniverſum peragravi orbem, uſque ad Indorum deſertos fines, ad eos quoque ſum profectus, qui arcto ſubjacent, &amp; Istri fontes, &amp; uſque Oceanum, ſum Saturni filius antiquior, germen ex pulchro &amp; generoſo ortum, cui genus non ſemen fuit, nec fuit in orbe locus quem non adinerim, docens ea quorum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventor fui.</q>
            </p>
            <p>After hee thus was quietly ſeated in his kingdome of Aegypt, his brother <hi>Typhon</hi> the Aegyptian (who in all vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanie &amp; mallice followed the humors of his father <hi>Cham</hi>) began now to repine and envie at the glorie and fortune of the Emperor <hi>Oſyris,</hi> in ſo much as he fell into a preſent conſpiracie with many other mallicious Gyants for the death and deſtruction of him and of his greatneſſe: which hee moſt traiterouſly proſecuted ſo far, as in the end, by ſubtill and craftie practiſes he entrapped him, who was by him and the reſt of the Gyants cruelly murdered and torn in peeces, whoſe bodie they divided, and had hewne out into ſix and twentie peeces, whereof every Gyant had a
<pb facs="tcp:9480:19"/>
ſhare and part, as a reward and ſatisfaction for ſuch their bloudie and victorious ſtratageme: but afterwards theſe parts of his bodie were found out and gathered together againe by the meanes of his wife <hi>Iſis,</hi> and buried, with their right honor and due ſolemnitie, whom after his death the Aegyptians held &amp; worſhipped as a god, as alſo the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Iſrael did the like in the deſart. <hi>Boccace</hi> ſayth, That hee was called alſo <hi>Serapis,</hi> and that the auncient Poets tearmed him likewiſe <hi>Dionyſius, Liber Pater,</hi> and <hi>Bacchus,</hi> and that hee was the firſt that ever triumphed, which was in the firſt voyage hee made into the Indies; and that the invention of garlands and crownes was by him deviſed.</p>
            <p>Our authour <hi>Beroſus</hi> by his collections ſeemeth to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadge, That this Emperour <hi>Oſyris</hi> was thus ſlaine in the prime and flower of his age, having attained onely unto three hundred yeares, for he was borne about the time of <hi>Ninus</hi> the third king of Babylon, and died in the raign of <hi>Baleus,</hi> the Babylonians eleventh king, by which it is very apparent, what woonderfull long time men in thoſe ages did live. His wife <hi>Iſis</hi> ſurvived him two hundred and foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore yeares, as hereafter ſhall bee mentioned, who after that ſhee had with all fit ceremonies and rites performed the funerals of her murdered husband, began nowe to thinke upon the actors thereof, and to meditate upon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge and direfull practiſes: whereupon ſhe convocateth all her children and nephewes, and inciteth them to the embracement of this her attempt and action, againſt the horrible murderers of her newly enterred husband. To be ſhort, they condiſcend to her motion, and in the field en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter with <hi>Typhon</hi> and his aſſociates, and in battell ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly ſubdue them: which victorie was atchieved hard by
<pb facs="tcp:9480:20"/>
the river Oris in Arabia, and in the ſame place where <hi>Oſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris</hi> himſelfe ſlew the mightie Gyant and tyrant <hi>Antheus.</hi> The world being thus delivered of the perverſe generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Cham, Iſis</hi> remained a peacefull and ſecure gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and queene over Aegypt, which ſhee compaſſed as well by her owne pollicies and deviſes, as by the valour and hardie proweſſe of her children, of which the cheefeſt and moſt valiant was called <hi>Hercules</hi> of Lybia, of whome now (withdrawing my pen for a while to ſpeake further of <hi>Iſis</hi>) I will more amply entreat.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hercules</hi> therefore, the moſt valourous and courage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous young prince, after hee had by this meanes revenged the death of his father <hi>Oſyris</hi> upon his uncle <hi>Typhon,</hi> and the reſt of his aſſociates, began now to have a feeling of this owne power and vigour, and undertaketh many moſt tedious voyages, to ſcour all places of the world from the tyrannie and oppreſſion of ſuch inhumane and impious tyrants: and firſt he paſſed through the province of Phoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicia, where he ſlew the tyrant <hi>Buſyris,</hi> the ſonne of him, whom <hi>Oſyris</hi> before had ſlaine. From thence he went into Phrygia, where Troy afterward was built, and there over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came the young tyrant <hi>Tipheus;</hi> and he gave the governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of that country to his own ſon <hi>Athus,</hi> which he begat of a ladie called <hi>Omphale,</hi> as hereafter ſhall bee declared. Likewiſe he vanquiſht the Gyant <hi>Mylinus,</hi> the younger king of the Iſland of Candia: and from thence hee came into Affrica, ſince called Barbaria, of which, hee named moſt part of it Lybia after his owne name, which before was called Phutea: and there in memory of his conqueſts hee erected a columne and ſtately pinacle. From hence paſſing through the ſtreights of Gibraltar, hee arrived in
<pb facs="tcp:9480:20"/>
Spaine, where upon his firſt landing, hee fought bodie to bodie againſt the three <hi>Gerions,</hi> which were brothers and joint commaunders and kings of Spaine, thoſe alſo hee overcame and ſlew, and created his ſonne <hi>Hiſpalus</hi> king and ruler of that countrey: which was now the ninth king thereof, and of whom the citie Hiſpalis, now called Sivile in Spaine, tooke her name and was ſo called. After this, <hi>Hercules</hi> determined to make a journey into Italie, there alſo to purchaſe further fame and reputation, by ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the tyrannie of thoſe that there then lived according to their owne will, power, and mightineſſe. In this his jor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney towards Italie by land, he paſſeth through the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome called Regnum Celticum, then called alſo Gaule, and at this day is knowne and nominated by the name of Fraunce: of the antiquitie of which countrey (before wee come to ſpeake of his arrivall in Italie) having ſo fit occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, we will in this place ſomething remember.</p>
            <p>Firſt therefore we muſt find out and know in what time and in what age this famous <hi>Hercules</hi> of Lybia paſſed through the countrey in this his journey, for ſo much as it is not written of any certainetie, or by any authenticke author, That hee ever journeied through this kingdome before, although ſome doe hold, That hee went that way into Spaine with his father <hi>Iupiter</hi> (ſurnamed <hi>Iuſtus</hi>) in the reigne of <hi>Lucus,</hi> the eight king of Gaule, as hath been be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſomewhat commemorated: and this matter may bee eaſily and evidently diſcovered, by comparing the times wherein <hi>Hiſpalus</hi> was eſtabliſhed and made king of Spain with thoſe ſucceeding, of which,<note place="margin">Johannes Annius.</note> 
               <hi>Iohannes Annius</hi> of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbe, a moſt excellent writer &amp; diligent Hyſtoriographer in his Chronicles of Spaine, ſayth, That the ſame <hi>Hiſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:9480:21"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:9480:21"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:9480:22"/>
was crowned and inveſted in the kingdome of Spaine by his father <hi>Hercules,</hi> in the ſix and thirtieth yeare of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leus</hi> (the ſecond of that name) the eleventh king of Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonia; which was after the floud five hundred foureſcore and ten years, before the foundation of Troy two hundred threeſcore and one, and before the incarnation of Chriſt a thouſand ſeven hundred and ſeven and twenty: for <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cules</hi> was born preſently after the death of <hi>Ninus,</hi> the third king of Babylon, from whoſe death unto the ſix and thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth yeare of <hi>Baleus,</hi> the eleventh king, were juſt two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred foureſcore and ten yeares: ſo that by this meanes it may clearely bee perceived, in what time and in what age this Lybian <hi>Hercules</hi> ſo arrived in Gaule, being preſently after the coronation of his ſonne <hi>Hiſpalus</hi> in Spaine. At this very time therefore of his comming into Gaule (which wee will now hereafter call Fraunce) reigned and governed in that countrey as their king and commander, one called by the name of <hi>Iupiter Celtes,</hi> the ſonne of king <hi>Lucus,</hi> whom before we a little touched, who exceeded all others in riches in thoſe dayes, and was marvellous weal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie in ſheepe, in cattell, and in paſturage, which were all the goods and poſſeſſions that princes in thoſe times a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounded in, in that countrey; for then ſilver or gold was not there known, jewels and rare ſtones were diſeſteemed, no tributes were paied, no taxes or impoſitions laid upon the ſubjects, all things without deceit, art, or any villanous invention of mans braine, were peaceably enjoyed. And to confirme this their ignorance of ſilver and ſuch mettals <hi>Diodorus Siculus</hi> thus ſayth, That the ſheepheards of this king <hi>Iupiter Celtes,</hi> attending their flockes on the top of thoſe mountaines which devide the kingdome of Fraunce
<pb facs="tcp:9480:22"/>
from that of Spaine, called Pyrenci, eſpied on the ſuddain on the one ſide of the furthermoſt hils, certaine liquid moiſture to run downe in haſtie ſtreames into the vallies below; and at the higher part of that mountaine, certaine flames of fire in moſt furious manner to ſhew themſelves, in ſo much, that very hard rockes and ſtonie ſubſtances on that mountaine were diſſolved and were melted with the extremitie of the heat and riſcaldation of thoſe fires: which alſo ceaſed not, but continued in that ſtrange ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner many moneths together. The ſilly and ſimple under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of theſe ſheepeheards, by no meanes aſſumed any apprehenſion of this ſo ſtraunge working of nature, but entertained it as a matter exceeding their capacitie and reach of judgement, and therefore paſſed it over with the leſſer woonder, in that they acknowledged in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſo deepe an imperfection and want of knowledge. But it ſo fortuned, That certaine merchants of Phoenicia travelling along thoſe coaſts, and perceiving that that mettal muſt needs be good which ſo diſtilled and tumbled downe from the tops of thoſe mountains (being, as many old writers alleadge, the mettall of ſilver) began to feele the diſpoſitions of thoſe all ignorant ſheepeheards, and to come to ſome compoſition and friendly tearmes for exchaunge of ſome wares they had, with that mettall, which thoſe hils in that plentie ſo affourded and yeelded forth. The poore ſheepeheards (as I told you before) not capable of the true value thereof, for matters of very little worth (which thoſe merchants then had) exchaunged the one for the other, without any ſuſpect of diſadvantage or ill bargaine on their ſides: and therupon the Phoenicians laded and fraughted their ſhips (then abiding in a port or
<pb facs="tcp:9480:23"/>
haven not farre of) with that mettall which thoſe ſilver mines ſo produced, and afterwards enriched their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey therewith in moſt abundant and plentifull manner: and by the reaſon of theſe fires, thoſe hils were afterwards entearmed and called Montes Pyrenaei, for Pyr in Greeke ſignifies Feu in French, and fire in Engliſh. But to returne from whence we digreſſed. This royall king, <hi>Iupiter Celtes</hi> which before wee remembered, had one onely daughter, which hee prized and endeared as his cheefeſt good; who exceeded all other ladies in the world, in proportion and ſtature, and in the graces of naturall beautie, and for that ſhe was of ſo extraordinarie and large talneſſe, ſhee was in thoſe daies held among thoſe people a Gyanteſſe. This ladie, whether proud of her own goodly features, or chaſt in her cogitations, could not by any meanes bee brought to affect any man whatſoever living, neither would her fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conſent to any match or mariage, that might be oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to take her from his ſight, and the fruition of her ſo deſired preſence, untill the comming of this ſo far-famou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and renowned <hi>Hercules</hi> of Lybia (of whoſe great wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe and ſtraunge performances, they had largely heard) they of themſelves intertained a new thought, and were eaſily induced, upon the firſt ſight of his perſonage (which was majeſticke and of wondrous grace) to unite their houſe with one of ſo noble demerit and of ſo gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall fame. <hi>Hercules</hi> likewiſe became ſo far enſnared with the gallant beautie, big proportion, and equiſit perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>Galathea</hi> (for ſo was the ladie called) that he inſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcovered the motions of his affections and love to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards her, which were reciprocally embraced and kindly entertained: ſo that there reſted onely the conſummation
<pb facs="tcp:9480:23"/>
of the nuptials, which were preſently after performed with all maner of ſolemnization and rites of ceremonies obſerved in thoſe dayes. Not long after the mariage of the Gianteſſe <hi>Galathea</hi> unto <hi>Hercules,</hi> her father <hi>Iupiter Celtes</hi> died, who for his vertuous life and good governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, was held in that reputation, eſteeme, &amp; reverence among thoſe people, that ever ſince that day, the third part of all that countrey of France is called after his own name Celtica. After him ſucceeded his ſonne in law <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cules,</hi> and tooke upon him the commaund and governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the countrey of Fraunce, living peaceably and proſperouſly with his wife <hi>Galathea</hi> many yeares, and taught alſo the people new courſes how to live, &amp; better cuſtomes and faſhions of behavior, controlling them for their rude and uncivile manners, and wholly depreſſing a moſt inhumane and impious order they had, of ſacrificing poore ſtrangers unto their gods, this hee aboliſhed and wholly extinguiſhed, enjoyning ſtreight lawes, &amp; puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for the violaters and infringers of ſuch his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement herein. Not long after, he built and erected a moſt gallant and mightie citie, which hee cauſed to bee ſeated on a high mountaine of that countrey, which now is called by the name of the Dutchie of Burgundie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Authun &amp; Langres, which citie he called Alexia, which interpreted, ſignifies conjunctive or uniting, to ſhew that there were two noble houſes of ſtraunge coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries conjoined and made one. This citie afterwards flouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in great glorie and puiſſance, and eſpecially in the times of <hi>Iulius Caeſar,</hi> before which, hee himſelfe with a moſt ſtrong armie lay, begirting the ſame with a moſt ſtrict &amp; hard ſiege: at which time, the giving of the flowers
<pb facs="tcp:9480:24"/>
de Luces in Fraunce tooke his originall, as <hi>Iulius Caeſar</hi> himſelfe in his ſeventh booke of his Commentaries affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth. But at this preſent, that once gallant and glorious citie of Alexia is but a mean village, and of ſmall account in the countrey of Lauxois not far from Flauigny.</p>
            <p>The great citie of Alexia thus in thoſe daies peopled, inhabited, and fortified by the great <hi>Hercules,</hi> the king of Gaule: after ſome orders and inſtitutions appointed for the good governance and managing of all things what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever at home, hee proceedeth in his entended voyage for Italie, and for that expedition raiſed a mightie and powerfull armie; with which, after hee had taken his leave of his wife <hi>Galathea,</hi> and of his young ſonne <hi>Galatheus,</hi> (now aged about foure yeares or thereabouts) he progreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to the effectuating of his firſt entendment, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently enters into the territories of the Allobroges (which countrey is now called Savoy) and there with main force of many hands and laborious ſouldiours, hee maketh his paſſage through thoſe wondrous high rockie mountains, in all ordinarie ſence and opinion then inacceſſible and not to be paſſed; but as the extreame induſtrie and pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of worke bringeth all difficult things in the end to obedience and commaund of art, ſo theſe undiſgeſted heapes of ſtubborne ſtones and rockes, were forced at the laſt to give way unto his armie, ſo far, that all their horſes and baggage whatſoever found a very plaine and eaſie paſſage. From thence he deſcended and came into Italy, where he fully revenged himſelfe of thoſe inhumane and lawleſſe Gyants, which were the death of his owne father <hi>Iupiter Iuſtus:</hi> and after all tumults quieted, and the reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants ſubdued, hee fell to preſcribe lawes to the people,
<pb facs="tcp:9480:24"/>
and to inſtruct them very carefully in matters of civile aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſociation &amp; orderly living: where we will for a while leave him, and once againe betake our ſelves more particularly to entreat of the firſt originall &amp; inhabitation of France: to begin with which, it muſt of neceſſitie be drawn by the lineall ſucceſſion and diſcent of father to ſon, even unto that <hi>Iupiter Celtes,</hi> and this <hi>Hercules</hi> of Lybia wee ſo lately remembred.</p>
            <p>It hath beene in the beginning of this booke related, how in the hundred yeare after the univerſall inundation and deluge of al things whatſoever which were contained in the wide embracement of the world, the good father and Patriarke <hi>Noe</hi> made his firſt voyage, and put foorth from Armenia with all thoſe his children, nephewes, and kinsfolkes, to diſcover unto them the ſituation of many other countries then unknowne: and that hee firſt paſſed over the Ponticke ſea, and ſo to the arme of the ſea Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terraneum, coaſting along the continent about all thoſe quarters; of purpoſe to ſhew unto his children the deviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the world, and Coſmographically to inſtruct them in the ſituation of each ſeverall countrey, as they ſtood and were inhabited before the floud: and after that, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionize unto his three firſt begotten ſonnes, every one his ſhare and allowance for his rule, commaund, and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, as hath been before alreadie ſpoken of. And in theſe his travels, hee brought alſo along with him many ſorts of beaſts, cattell, hearbes, and other ſuch things that were availeable for the encreaſe and maintenance of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane life; and with every one of his children or kinsfolke left a certaine allowance of ſuch things, there to multiply and engender. In this his firſt perigrination, he came into
<pb facs="tcp:9480:25"/>
Gaule, and ſo into Italie, where after hee had ſpent ſome time, hee returned backe into Armenia, about the tenth yeare he had ſet forth from thence: by which it may bee gathered, that Gaule was firſt inhabited and peopled in the hundred and eight yeare after the generall floud.</p>
            <p>After this his returne into Armenia, having there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted himſelfe ſome one and twentie yeares, hee began to invent the foundations of great citties, and to eſtabliſh kingdomes and ſiegnories throughout the world: ſo that in the hundred and two and thirtieth year after the deluge he firſt erected and appointed the monarchie of the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylonians, of which, the firſt king was called <hi>Nembroth, Noes</hi> couſin: and about the thirteenth yeare of the raigne of this <hi>Nembroth,</hi> hee inſtituted and eſtabliſhed for the king of the Gaules one other of his kinſmen called <hi>Samo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes,</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Dis,</hi> the fourth ſonne of <hi>Iaphet,</hi> a man very wiſe and well governed. <hi>Samothes</hi> therefore accordingly tooke his leave of the Patriarke <hi>Noe,</hi> his grandmother <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tea,</hi> of his father <hi>Iaphet,</hi> and of his mother <hi>Noegla</hi> and the reſt of his kindred, and ſet forward toward his kingdome and governement with all expedition poſſible: carying along with him diverſe ſorts of cattell, poultrey, and other things neceſſarie for the maintaining and conſervation of mankind (which kind of things were all the riches &amp; trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures that men deſired to poſſeſſe in thoſe daies:) and thus with all his traine, familie, and followers, hee taketh ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping in the ſea called Marc major, and in the end, by the favorable aſſiſtance of proſperous winds, he arrived with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the confines of Gaule, which was ſome ſeven &amp; thirtie yeares after his firſt being there with his grandfather <hi>Noe,</hi> and about eightſcore and foure yeares after the deluge:
<pb facs="tcp:9480:25"/>
by which it may bee underſtood, That this <hi>Samothes</hi> the fourth ſonne of <hi>Iaphet,</hi> was little leſſe than ſeven ſcore yeares of age, when he now laſt viſited the countrey.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Samothes</hi> therfore now entred into his own kingdome with his wife, children, and followers, and alſo his horſes, kine, and other things neceſſarie, began to ſettle himſelfe therein, and to give out edicts and breefe commaunds what he would have done and performed in this his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey: which was done in the yeare after the floud above written, and about two thouſand foureſcore and thirteene yeares before the incarnation of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. The countrey was very much peopled by this time, and great encreaſes of all other things there were found upon his now comming (for it was now ſeven and thirty yeares paſt ſince <hi>Noe</hi> left people there firſt to inhabit and multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie, which in ſuch a time grew to great abundance of all things whatſoever.) His welcome and entertainement was wonderous gladly accepted of thoſe people and men of the countrey, who acknowledged him as their Lord, their Patriarke, their cheefe, and their <hi>Saturne;</hi> which names in thoſe daies were given as titles only of honor, excellence, and dignitie, as <hi>Zenophon</hi> in his Aequivocals alſo ſayth: <q>Saturni dicuntur familiarium nobilium regum, qui urbes condiderunt Primogeniti eorum, vocantur Ioves, &amp; Iunones: vero Nepotes eorum Hercules fortiſsimi &amp; cetera.</q>
            </p>
            <p>It may now very well bee imagined, that thoſe people having ſo long time lived without a governour, king, or particular commaunder, muſt of neceſſitie bee very rude,
<pb facs="tcp:9480:26"/>
uncivile, obſtinat, and barbarous, living onely according to the lawes of Nature, and following their owne wils, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, and concupiſcence. Yet notwithſtanding, <hi>Samothes</hi> by faire and gentle demeanures &amp; mild cariages, ſo woon their hearts unto him, that they became eaſily reclaimed, and brought to be docible and obedient to what precepts or commaunds were impoſed upon them: and upon this hee deviſed lawes and ordinances for domeſticke conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, which he cauſed to bee made plaine unto the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who at the firſt ſomething wondered at ſo ſtraunge al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terations, having ſo many yeares together lived without any cheefe, or any lawes to curbe or bridle their naturall fantaſies and diſordinat affections. And theſe lawes were made in the fourth yeare of the raigne of <hi>Ninus,</hi> the third king of Babylon, at what time alſo <hi>Tuyſcon</hi> the Gyant, his uncle, king of Almaigne, and <hi>Tuball</hi> king of Spaine, did the like, inſtructing their people very induſtriouſly in the rules of Philoſophie, Phyſicke, and Aſtronomie, which they themſelves had learned of their grandfather <hi>Noe</hi> and their father <hi>Iaphet.</hi> And if it bee here demaunded, what kind of writings they then uſed, <hi>Beroſas</hi> doth anſwere, that they were certaine Phoenician characters &amp; letters (which alſo were uſed in Armenia) which were very like unto thoſe which <hi>Cadmus</hi> long time after brought from Phoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicia into Greece, and therefore <hi>Iulius Caeſar</hi> in his ſixt booke of Commentaries ſayth, That the Gaules did uſe in thoſe times Greeke letters for their manner of writing: but undoubtedly, thoſe characters were found long time before they were ever knowne in Greece, as <hi>Zenophon</hi> and many other authors confidently doe affirme.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Samothes,</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Dis,</hi> living thus in all tranquilitie
<pb facs="tcp:9480:26"/>
and peaceable ſecuritie among his people, ceaſed not dayly to poſſeſſe their hearts with ſtrong opinions of the worth and value of learning, for it is written, that hee was the wiſeſt and moſt learned prince in the world in thoſe times, as <hi>Beroſus</hi> alſo alloweth, when he thus ſayth:
<q>Samothes, qui &amp; Dis vocatur, Celtas colonias fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>davit, nec erat quis etate illa iſto ſapientior, ac propterea Samothes dictus eſt.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Among other his rules of Philoſophie and learning, one was (beeing the cheefeſt) hee taught the people, That the ſoules of men were immortall; which before they hardly beleeved, as men dwelling in the ſhade of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and invelloped with darke miſts of errour. After he had thus eſtabliſhed lawes and ordinances for the good governement of his country, and all his people enjoying peaceably the fruits of quietneſſe: after the end of ſeven and fortie yeares, he rendered up unto Nature that debt which could not be any longer kept backe and detained; and left his eldeſt ſonne (called <hi>Magus</hi>) inherit or unto his kingdome and governement, which was in the one and fiftieth yeare of the raigne of <hi>Nynus</hi> the third king of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon, and when his father <hi>Samothes</hi> had commaunded that countrey ſevenſcore &amp; five yeares, being at his death about three hundred yeares of age, or much thereabout. This <hi>Samothes</hi> was of that eſteeme in thoſe dayes, and ſo generally reverenced and loved for his vertues through all that countrey, that the Gaulois or Frenchmen, even unto the time of <hi>Iulius Caeſar,</hi> boaſted and gloried of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo much, as that they were deſcended and iſſued
<pb facs="tcp:9480:27"/>
from him, ſo highly was he poſſeſt of the peoples hearts, in the greateſt opinion of trueſt love, the which thing alſo <hi>Iulius Caeſar</hi> in the ſixt booke of his Commentaries more copiouſly remembreth. In his time alſo the ſects of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophie firſt tooke their beginning and originall in Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope, and were called Samothees, which were men ſtudied and expert in all letters, humane and divine; contrarie to the opinion of many, who write, that Greece was the firſt mother and bringer forth of arts and ſciences. But <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genes Laertius,</hi> in the beginning of his booke entituled, The lives of the Philoſophers, contradicteth thoſe ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, ſaying: <hi>Philoſophiam à Barbaris initia ſumpſiſſe complures auctores aſserunt, conſtat enim apud Perſas claru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſe Magos, apud Babilonios &amp; Aſsirios floruiſſe Caldeos, apud Celtas &amp; Gallos Druidas, &amp; qui Samothei dicuntur. Magus,</hi> the eldeſt ſonne of the Patriarke and <hi>Saturne, Samothes</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Dis,</hi> began now to take upon him the rule and commaund of this his countrey ſo left unto him by rightfull ſucceſſion from his father, in the three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeare after the floud, after the nativitie of the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arke <hi>Abraham</hi> eight yeares, and before the birth of Chriſt two thouſand and ſeventeene yeares. This <hi>Magus</hi> was a prince of great wiſedome, learning and judgement, and alſo a great builder, as the interpretation of his name delivereth us: for this word <hi>Magus,</hi> in the Scythian toung ſignifieth a builder or erecter; and in the Perſian language, a Philoſopher or a wiſe man. And <hi>Beroſus</hi> in his booke of Time thus ſayth of him: <hi>Nini LI. anno, apud Celtas regna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit Samothis filius Magus, à quo oppida plurima poſita ſunt in ea regione:</hi> by which it may be gathered, that hee was the firſt that ever in that country cauſed any villages, cities
<pb facs="tcp:9480:27"/>
townes or houſes to bee built and erected, for before that time men lived altogether in the fields, under the umbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of trees and covertures of ſome pleaſant groves. <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hannes Annius di Viterba</hi> in his Commentaries upon <hi>Beroſus,</hi> ſayth, That this word <hi>Magus</hi> ſignifieth in that tongue which firſt was uſed in that countrey of Gaule, as much, as a pallace, houſe, or manſion: which opinion challengeth unto it ſelfe the ſtronger probabilitie, for that with <hi>Ptolomie</hi> in his Coſmographie you ſhall find; that moſt of the moſt auncient townes in that country ended with this word <hi>Magus:</hi> as in Aquitaine, Noviomagus; in the province of Lyons, Neomagus; in Gallia Belgica, Rhotomagus, which is now the citie of Roan in Norman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die: there is alſo Berbetomagus, Vindomagus, and many others, whoſe names doe end in this word <hi>Magus;</hi> as alſo Nimegham in Guelderland, was called likewiſe Novio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magus. By all theſe inſtances it is made apparent, that this <hi>Magus,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Samothes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Magus</hi> king of Fraunce the firſt that ever built townes in that coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them to be inhabited</note> was the firſt that reduced &amp; gathered together the people of that countrey into villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, townes, and boroughs. And further, either of his life, or the certaine time or continuance of his raigne and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernement, it hath not been by any allowed author or an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient writer capitulated.</p>
            <p>After <hi>Magus,</hi> ſucceeded one of his ſons called <hi>Sarron,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sarron</hi> king of Fraunce, the firſt fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities.</note> the third king of Fraunce, who excelled in the ſtudie of letters, and governed his people with great mildnes, cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie, and uprightneſſe; and he was the firſt that erected univerſities or publicke ſchooles of learning: and of him alſo came a ſect of Philoſophers called <hi>Sarronides,</hi> as <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorus Siculus</hi> in his ſixt booke of Antiquities affirmeth, thus ſaying: <hi>Sunt apud Celtas Theologi, ac Philoſophi quos
<pb facs="tcp:9480:28"/>
vocant Sarronidas, qui precipue ab eis coluntur, nam moris eſt apud illos nullum abſque Philoſopho ſacrificium facere, &amp;c.</hi> For in thoſe daies Philoſophers and men of learning were regarded with great reverence, zeale, and gracious reſpect; and nothing there, of any import was concluded or agreed upon without their privities conſent or aduiſe therein.</p>
            <p>Vnto the kingdome of Fraunce after <hi>Sarron,</hi> came <hi>Drijus, Sarrons</hi> eldeſt ſonne, unto whom <hi>Beroſus</hi> aſcribeth this title: <hi>Apud Celtas Drijus peritiae plenus.</hi> Hee began to raigne foure hundred and tenne yeares after the generall deluge, which was about two hundred five &amp; fiftie yeares after the firſt foundation and inhabitation of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Fraunce. Hee was deepely ſeene in principles of Philoſophie, &amp; very skilfull in many other ſciences. And it is very credibly delivered by many very grave and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned writers, that he built the cittie of Dreux in Norman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, and that of his name came the ſect of Philoſophers, which were called Druydes, which were wondrous lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Divines, Augurers, Magicians, and Sacrificers: but ſuch their oblations and ſacrifices in theſe their dayes of blindneſſe, were performed with ſuch inhumane and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly faſhions, with the effuſion and ſhedding of human bloud in that lamentable and cruell manner, as is too ſtraunge to be reported: which unnaturall and impious cuſtome, was aboliſhed and cleane put downe by the firſt Romane Emperours, <hi>Augustus,</hi> and <hi>Divus Claudius,</hi> as <hi>Suetonius Tranquilius, Iulius Caeſar,</hi> and <hi>Plinie,</hi> more directly have particularized the ſame.</p>
            <p>After the death of this king <hi>Drijus,</hi> his ſonne (called <hi>Bardus</hi>) raigned in his place, &amp; was the fift king of France. This <hi>Bardus</hi> was the firſt deviſer and inventor of rimes,
<pb facs="tcp:9480:28"/>
ſongs, and Muſicke, of whome the Poets and Rhethorici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans firſt tooke their ſect, which were called alſo Bardes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bardus</hi> king of Fraunce firſt inve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tor of Poetrie.</note> as <hi>Diodorus Siculus</hi> in his ſixt booke more at large remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breth. And theſe Poets and ſingers were held in that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verenced regard in thoſe times among thoſe people, that if upon the inſtant encounter of the battels of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies on both parts, theſe Poets had ſtept and put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in betweene both the armies, they had for that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent time recalled their furious intendments, and beene mollified with the pleaſant perſuaſive tongues of theſe eloquent Rhethoricians and ſweet-ſinging Poets, as <hi>Bero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> in one place ſayth to the ſame purpoſe: <hi>Etiam apud agreſtiores barbaros ira cedit ſapientiae &amp; Mars reveretur muſas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The debt due unto Nature being fully ſatisfied by this king <hi>Bardus</hi> (for no quillit or evacuation whatſoever may avoid it) his eldeſt ſonne called <hi>Longho</hi> was called upon to undertake that which his father had left hereditarie unto him: of whome, no extraordinarie memorable thing is left by fame unto the ſonnes of time, nor any authoritie of any great antiquarie poſſeſſeth us with his worthineſſe vertues or perfections: it is only ſuppoſed, that before his death he built the citie of Langres, which we call in Latin <hi>Civitas Lingonenſis.</hi> And hee had a ſonne called <hi>Bardus</hi> the younger, which was the ſeventh king of Fraunce, and began to commaund ſome three hundred and one and fortie yeares after the foundation and enpeopling of this countrey of Fraunce. And it is very probable, That of theſe two kings <hi>Longho</hi> and <hi>Bardus,</hi> the firſt originall and beginning of the people called Lombards took their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and name, for they are entearmed in Latine Longo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bardi,
<pb facs="tcp:9480:29"/>
which nation, although at the firſt they were extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and deſcended out of Almaign (now called Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie) yet they bare domination and rule for the ſpace of two hundred yeares and more in Italie, even untill the time of king <hi>Charlemaine,</hi> who abſolutely deprived them of all commaund, power, and authoritie in that countrey round about.</p>
            <p>The eight king of Fraunce, was <hi>Lucus,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Bardus</hi> the younger, of whom it is written (as <hi>Ptolomy</hi> and others doe affirme) the people called Luces or Lucenſes (ſince inhabiting about the cittie of Paris) tooke their name and originall. Of him alſo, writers have beene very ſparing to ſpeake of, more than that hee begat a ſon called <hi>Iupiter Celtes,</hi> the ninth king of Fraunce, and father to the faire and beautious gyanteſſe <hi>Galathea,</hi> whom before wee ſo largely ſpoke of and remembred. And it is by compu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and due reckoning found, that ſince the firſt <hi>Saturn</hi> and king of Fraunce called <hi>Samothes</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Dis,</hi> unto the raign of <hi>Iupiter Celtes,</hi> were about four hundred years. And now having thus lineally drawne the ſucceſſion of every king of this countrey, ſince the firſt inhabitation thereof untill this <hi>Iupiter Celtes,</hi> and ſo conſequently unto his ſonne in law, <hi>Hercules</hi> of Lybia, now the tenth king of Fraunce; we will proceed with him (now employed about his affaires in Italie) and with his iſſue and poſteritie, as it is delivered by authours of great worth, learning, and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie.</p>
            <p>It hath been before ſomewhat touched, how <hi>Hercules</hi> paſſing through thoſe mountainous places of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey of Savoy, at length arrived in Italie, where (having a puiſſant armie) hee preſently fell to wars with the Gyants
<pb facs="tcp:9480:29"/>
called <hi>Leſtrigones,</hi> moſt bloudie, cruell, and oppreſſive ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, and the murderers or conſenting aidants unto the death of his father <hi>Oſyris</hi> (ſurnamed <hi>Iupiter Iuſtus.</hi>) With theſe powerfull commaunders in that countrey, he enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained many fights, and found them very reſolute, &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to endure the uttermoſt of his mightineſſe and ſtrength: yet in the end, after a ten yeares wars he victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly triumphed over them, and utterly razed out all their iſſue and poſteritie whatſoever: and the place wherein his laſt battell againſt theſe Gyants, was fought in, retaineth ſtill his old name, and is yet called, The valley of the Gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants; which is hard adjoyning unto the cittie called Tuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canella in Tuſcania. Theſe civile &amp; inteſtine broiles being thus valiantly and ſucceſſefully appeaſed, <hi>Hercules</hi> remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned a quiet and peaceable poſſeſſor of all the countrey of Italie, wherein he raigned and continued for the ſpace of twenty yeares, much about the time that his father <hi>Oſyris,</hi> his grandfather <hi>Cham,</hi> and his great grandfather <hi>Noe,</hi> had there commaunded: in which time hee beſtowed many gracious and commodious good turnes upon the people of that countrey, and built and erected many gallant and famous cities, although the moſt part of them bee at this day by the all conſuming tyrannie of Time ruinated, ſpoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and decayed. He alſo at this time cauſed the Iſland of Sardinia to be peopled, frequented, and inhabited, which untill that time lay waſt, depopulate, and barbarous: and in this place hee appointed a ruler called <hi>Iolaus</hi> to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund as under him, that countrey, and thoſe people ſo committed unto him. Hee likewiſe cauſed through moſt part of Italie (eſpecially in the mooriſh &amp; wetteſt places thereof) many ditches and trenches to bee caſt up, that
<pb facs="tcp:9480:30"/>
thereby the palludious meres and ſtanding lakes, might find paſſages to emptie their flouds, and that the fields and baſtures by that meanes might be preſerved drie, and be made more fit for agriculture, tillage, and other neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie encreaſes for the generall profit and good of all the whole countrey thereabouts: and of him the river Arnus taketh name, for <hi>Hercules</hi> was alſo ſurnamed <hi>Muſarnus:</hi> and he lived for the moſt part of the time that he ſpent in that countrey, in a cittie called Feſula in Tuſcania, which citie even at this day (though not in that glory as hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) giveth the armes of <hi>Hercules.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Italie being thus freed from the ſervitude wherein it lived of thoſe ungodly and uncivile Gyants, and beeing now brought to a generall quietneſſe, eaſe, and proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous eſtate, <hi>Hercules</hi> determined with himſelfe to ſend for both of his eldeſt ſonnes, to eſtabliſh the one in the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalitie of Italie, &amp; the other in the kingdome of France; and hee to take his journey once againe into Spaine (to which countrey hee was much addicted) there to live pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately, and to ſpend the reſt of his yeares to come, in peace pleaſantneſſe, and in all content. Whereupon hee diſpat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched meſſengers to his wife <hi>Galathea</hi> (then remaining in Fraunce, as hath been before ſpoken of) to ſend him pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently his ſonne <hi>Galatheus,</hi> being now of mans eſtate, and very able to beare armes. Other meſſengers were diſpat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched into Scythia (now called Tartaria) there to ſeek out his eldeſt ſonne <hi>Tuſcus,</hi> then remaining with the queene <hi>Araxa,</hi> queene of Scythia, inhabiting thoſe countries which lie upon the floud Tanais, and by the moores and water-lakes called Meotides. Vpon the commandement of king <hi>Hercules, Galathea</hi> his wife preſently ſent unto
<pb facs="tcp:9480:30"/>
him his ſon <hi>Galatheus</hi> into Italie, accompanied with the greateſt men of Fraunce, who was very joyouſly welcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med unto his father with great feaſts and ſignes of glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: for he was now growne up unto a gallant big pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of bodie and comely feature, and was alſo of a very gentle and gracious diſpoſition, mild in his demea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nures, and yet majeſticall and of a ſpirit-promiſing aſpect, throughout all his countenance. Not long after him arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved his elder brother <hi>Tuſcus</hi> from Tartaria, who alſo was of a mightie corpulencie and extraordinarie large ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, whom indeed <hi>Hercules</hi> had begot in the very prime of his youth and vigorous luſtineſſe. Vpon the meeting of theſe two, a great court or aſſembly of great lords and princes was held in all pompe, glorie, and magnificence: where, in the preſence of all the noble Lords and Barons of diverſe countries and governments, as of Aegypt, Lybia (now called Affrica) Spaine, Fraunce, Italie, and Tartaria, with great ſolemnities, rites, and ceremonies, <hi>Tuſcus</hi> was created and eſtabliſhed the ſole king, <hi>Saturne,</hi> and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunder of all the countrey of Italie, and hee was there inveſted in the dignitie of <hi>Ceritus,</hi> that is as much to ſay, as <hi>Iupiter</hi> crowned, or Patriarke of Tuſcania: &amp; the yonger brother <hi>Galatheus,</hi> aged about ſix and thirtie yeares or thereabouts, was preferred alſo at that time unto the rule and governement of the kingdome of Fraunce. All which ceremonies were performed with great triumph, ſtate, and royaltie, and kept in the citie of Viterba, in the yeare after the univerſall inundation of the world, ſix hundred and five and twentie, before the foundation of Troy nineſcore and one yeares, and before the incarnation of Chriſt a thouſand ſix hundred fortie eight. Theſe things thus ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnely
<pb facs="tcp:9480:31"/>
conſummated, and <hi>Hercules</hi> voluntarily diſpoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſing himſelfe of theſe two ſuch imperiall crowns. After he had delivered ſome inſtructions &amp; principles of good government to theſe new erected kings, <hi>Tuſcus</hi> and <hi>Gala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theus,</hi> after a generall conge of them all, he took his jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney towards Spaine, to the great diſcontent and greeſe of all the cheefe Barons, and alſo of the Plebeians, through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all the countrey of Italie: but beeing now arrived in Spaine, he found his ſon <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſpalus,</hi> which hee himſelfe had before eſtabliſhed in that kingdome, to be dead, who had reigned onely ſeventeene yeares: and that after him ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded his nephew <hi>Hiſpanus,</hi> the ſeventeenth king of Spaine, and the firſt of that name, who called the country after his owne name, Hiſpania, which name it ever ſince hath retained: for before that time it was called H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>beria. This <hi>Hiſpanus</hi> raigned afterwards ſome two and thirtie yeares or neare thereabouts, as moſt writers and Crono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphers of Spaine doe agree. And in this kings raigne, about the nineteenth yeare thereof (as is before written) arrived <hi>Hercules</hi> in that countrey, now very aged, and of many yeares, where hee continued three yeares with his nephew, without any command or place, in as great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, eaſe, and quiet as might bee, for hee had now given over the deſire of rule and principalitie, and gloried in nothing ſo much, as that he by his owne valour, proweſſe, and labours, had conquered ſuch gallant countries to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of as hee himſelfe thought good, and to give to his children to enjoy as their rightful inheritances: for indeed hee was the Monarch and prince almoſt of all the world, and had attained unto ſuch his height of glorie and fame, not by oppreſſions, tyrannie, or unlawfulneſſe, but by the
<pb facs="tcp:9480:31"/>
ſubduing of wicked and ungodly gyants, the depoſing of all uſurpers and bloudie governours, &amp; by the aboliſhing and rooting out of all divelliſh and inhumane cuſtomes then obſerved in thoſe daies among the poore and faith-wanting vulgars in thoſe times of error. In theſe his times of privateneſſe and retired living which he ſpent in Spain, he builded and cauſed to bee erected many great townes, citties, and villages; for which cauſe the people of that countrey ſtill call him <hi>Hercules</hi> the builder. Beſides this, alſo hee gave and addicted himſelfe to the finding out of the natures of ſtrange hearbs, and to the ſtudie of Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomie, and the Magicke art, where in he wondrous deeply was ſeene, and excellently well read; but hee never applied the uſe thereof but unto the good and generall commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie of the countrey. Hee found out many remedies and enchauntments againſt the poyſon of ſerpents and many other venomous beaſts, then abounding in that countrie in great plentie, and by which the inhabitants before were greevouſly moleſted and exceedingly troubled. Hee alſo performed there many other memorable things of great worth, value, and import, as <hi>Higinus</hi> and many other very learned writers doe affirme. Not long after, his nephew <hi>Hiſpanus,</hi> king of Spaine, died without iſſue, &amp; left none of his owne bloud to inherite the kingdome after him: whereupon by the generall entreatie of all the whole land, and by publicke conſent, the command and government of that countrey was impoſed upon <hi>Hercules,</hi> whome the people for his vertues, faire demeanures, and good go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, did indeed very highly affect and reverence: and here (having ſo fit an occaſion to ſpeake of the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall and antiquitie of this countrey of Spaine) wee will
<pb facs="tcp:9480:32"/>
for a while leave him, undertaking the charge once again and the commaund and governement thereof: and we will begin with the firſt king of Spaine, and ſo by ſucceſſion and lineall deſcent from one to another, as far as <hi>Beroſus, Euſebius, Solynus,</hi> and <hi>Diodorus Siculus</hi> have proceeded therein, and untill wee come to the raigne of this <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cules.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The very firſt inhabitation and peopling of this coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey of Spaine, was by thoſe people that came from the other ſide of the Caſpian ſea, called Iberi, Perſae, Pheni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and Paeni, as <hi>Plinie</hi> in the third booke of his naturall hyſtorie doth alleadge; as alſo <hi>Marcus Varro,</hi> and <hi>Cato</hi> in his originals doe affirme the ſame; wholly condemning the Grecians of vaine glorie and ignorance, to write, that <hi>Hercules, Pirenes, Luſus,</hi> and <hi>Pan</hi> were the firſt that ever inhabited in this countrey: but of the colonies therefore of thoſe people before mentioned, it is very certain, that Spaine took firſt her originall, as alſo thoſe other Iſlands round about, is called Sicilia, Corſica, Sardinia, and Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leares: and the Iſland Corſica was ſo called of the people Corſi, which the Grecians tearme Cyrnum or Cyrum, but the Perſians and Hebrewes Corſum: and after theſe people, the Gothes and Alani came and lived in Spaine long time, and continued for the moſt part of them untill this very preſent wherein wee now live, from whome and from the reſt before mentioned, it is delivered for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine by many auncient, grave, and learned writers, this countrey of Spain deriveth her firſt beginning and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall foundation.</p>
            <p>S. <hi>Ierome, Euſebius, Ioſephus,</hi> and many other approved good authors, doe all conſent and agree, That <hi>Tuball</hi> the
<pb facs="tcp:9480:32"/>
fift ſonne of <hi>Iaphet,</hi> the ſon of <hi>Noe,</hi> was the firſt that ever was called by the name of king in that country of Spain, and that he was alſo the firſt that erected &amp; built townes and cities, and preſcribed bounds and limits in the ſame; which as <hi>Beroſus</hi> ſayth, was after the floud a hundred three and fortie yeares, and in the twelfth yeare of the raigne of <hi>Nembroth,</hi> the Babylonians <hi>Saturne</hi> and ruler; which was before the foundation of Troy ſix hundred thirtie ſeven yeares, and before the nativitie of Chriſt two thouſand two hundred yeares. The great citie which he called after his owne name (Tuball) is in Baetica, as <hi>Pomponius Mela</hi> affirmeth, as alſo <hi>Strabo</hi> averreth the ſame. This kings cheefe ſtudie and delight was in paſturage, in flockes of ſheepe, and heards of cattell, wherein in thoſe times men repoſed great contentment, pleaſure, and felicitie: &amp; ſuch his ſtudie the people (called Arameans) entearmed by the name of Tharaconem, which is as much to ſay, as <hi>Paſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum congreationem,</hi> The meeting together or aſſembly of ſheepeheards, as S. <hi>Ierome</hi> and the Thalmudiſts of the Iewes interprets it: and of the ſame the great citie of Tha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racona is called, as Saguntum firſt tooke her name of <hi>Sagus,</hi> the builder and erecter thereof. He began alſo firſt to ſet downe lawes, precepts, and directions unto his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and to poſſeſſe them with the opinion of good obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience unto their prince, and perſuaded them by fair and gentle meanes to the embracement of a civile and quiet life and converſation: and this, <hi>Beroſus</hi> ſaith was perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and done in the fourth yeare of <hi>Ninus</hi> king of Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon, as before in ſome places hath been a little remembe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: and <hi>Strabo</hi> ſayth, That in the tenth yeare of the ſame <hi>Ninus</hi> king of Babylon, and in the age of <hi>Tuball</hi> one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
<pb facs="tcp:9480:33"/>
and fifteene yeares, <hi>Noe</hi> (ſurnamed <hi>Ianus</hi>) comming out of Affrica and Phoenicia, arrived in Spain, &amp; brought thither with him two colonies, called Nooelas and Nooe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glas; although <hi>Plinie</hi> in his third booke of naturall hyſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, in the ſix and twentieth chapter thereof calleth them Nooegas and Nooelas: and in this countrey were they planted, and remained with great multiplication, encreaſe and abundance. This <hi>Tuball</hi> raigned in this his governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, untill the nine and fortieth yeare of the raigne of <hi>Ninus,</hi> and from the firſt inhabitation of Spain a hundred and five and fiftie yeares:<note place="margin">The Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arke <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> borne.</note> and in this kings governement was the Patriarke <hi>Abraham</hi> borne, which was juſt by all neareſt computation, towards the end of his raigne, and in the foure and fortieth yeare of the before ſpecified <hi>Ninus</hi> king of Babylon.</p>
            <p>Vnto <hi>Tuball</hi> ſucceeded his ſonne called <hi>Iberus,</hi> in the government and kingdome which he had left him to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy: which was from the floud two hundred ninetie &amp; nine yeares, from the firſt enpeopling of Spain a hundred fiftie ſix, before the erection of Troy five hundred thirtie and one, and before the birth of Chriſt two thouſand and ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene yeares.<note place="margin">Marcus Varro.</note> And of this <hi>Iberus</hi> (as <hi>Marcus Varro</hi> allead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth) the countrey was generally called Iberia, as it was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards Celtiberia, of certaine people called Celtes, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habiting long after in Fraunce, as many authentike hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorians doe affirme: and of this king alſo the river Iberus tooke her name,<note place="margin">Solynus.</note> and was ſo called. This floud, as <hi>Solynus, Albertus Magnus,</hi> and <hi>Diodorus Siculus</hi> averre, beginneth his firſt Spring, and taketh his head under the hils called Montes Pyrenaei, which lately before we remembred, and from thence runs winding and crooked like the ſhape of a
<pb facs="tcp:9480:33"/>
ſerpent or ſnake through the promontorie of Feraria, and ſo tumbleth downe amaine into the ſea called Pelagus Beleare. And this king <hi>Iberus</hi> raigned untill the three and thirtieth yeare of the rule of <hi>Semiramis,</hi> which is about ſeven and thirtie yeares or much thereabouts, as <hi>Euſebius</hi> accounteth it.</p>
            <p>The third king of Spaine, according to the opinion of moſt hyſtorians, was <hi>Iubalda,</hi> of whoſe name the hill cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Iubalda, was ſo called, as <hi>Beroſus</hi> affirmeth, although in <hi>Ptolomie</hi> it is written Iubeda,<note place="margin">Ptolomie.</note> and by the ſucceſſions of times, corruptibly Gybaltar, by which name at this time the countrey doth acknowledge it. This <hi>Iubalda</hi> began to enter into his kingdome in the foure and thirtieth year of the raign of <hi>Semiramis:</hi> from the worlds inundation three hundred thirtie ſix, from the birth of the holy Patriarke <hi>Abraham</hi> foure and fortie, from the firſt inhabitation of Spain two hundred wanting ſeven years, before the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Troy foure hundred foureſcore and foure yeares, and before the birth of our Saviour Chriſt one thouſand nine hundred foureſcore and one yeares. And in this kings raigne the ever-famouſed <hi>Hercules</hi> of Lybia was borne, which was before the birth of the Grecian <hi>Hercules,</hi> of whom ſo many grave authors have written and beene de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, almoſt ſeven hundred yeares: of the difference of which, becauſe it hath bred ſuch an incurable skar of error among very learned and old writers, I think it ſhall not be much impertinent in this place ſomething to particula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rize. Of the number therefore of thoſe men which were called by the name of <hi>Hercules,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Varro.</note> 
               <hi>Varro</hi> and many other au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors alleadge to bee at the leaſt three and fortie ſeverall names, but the moſt famous &amp; renowmed were only two,
<pb facs="tcp:9480:34"/>
of which, the firſt and moſt worthie was called <hi>Egiptius Thebanus,</hi> or <hi>Hercules Licicus;</hi> the ſecond, <hi>Alcaeus Graecus,</hi> the ſon of <hi>Alcmena</hi> and <hi>Amphitrio,</hi> as <hi>Diodorus Siculus, Herodotus,</hi> and many others affirme, who report alſo, That there was a temple in Phoenicia built and dedicated unto the firſt <hi>Hercules</hi> many years before the comming of this <hi>Hercules Graecus,</hi> the ſon of <hi>Amphitrio,</hi> and that alſo long after both theſe two (with the ancient Grecians) were held and worſhipped in great reverence and adoration; but the one of them, being <hi>Hercules Egiptius</hi> (ſay they) was adored as a god, the other but as a mightie and famous conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour. <hi>Cicero</hi> in his booke entituled <hi>de natura Deorum,</hi> ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth downe this <hi>Hercules</hi> alſo as a god, as <hi>Macrobius</hi> alſo and many others have opinionated the ſame. <hi>Diodorus Siculus</hi> in his firſt booke confidently alleadgeth, That this <hi>Hercules Graecus</hi> had not to name <hi>Hercules,</hi> which ſignifies heartie, but that his proper name was <hi>Alceus</hi> and alſo <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raclius,</hi> which interpreted, ſignifies <hi>Iunonis gloria:</hi> which opinion likewiſe <hi>Herodotus</hi> conſenteth with, when in his ſecond booke of hyſtories hee affirmeth, that this word <hi>Hercules</hi> is not a Greeke word, but of the Aegyptian lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, and that the Grecians afterwards ſtole it from the right owner thereof, and unworthily attributed it unto this <hi>Alceus,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Amphitrio:</hi> which thing alſo <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebius</hi> maintaineth, and ſayth, That thoſe famous and gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant exploits wherewith the world was ſo long poſſeſſed, and caried ſuch univerſall admirations among all men, were miſplaced and beſtowed on a ſtraunger, that came not neare the true merit and worthineſſe of him whom it truly concerned; thereby cleane exempting &amp; excepting this <hi>Alceus (Amphitrios</hi> ſonne) from all interreſt or right
<pb facs="tcp:9480:34"/>
unto any theſe ſo high and wonder-worthy performances, as only particular and belonging unto this noble <hi>Hercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les Egiptius</hi> or <hi>Libicus,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Oſyris,</hi> called <hi>Iupiter Iuſtus</hi> (as <hi>Diodorus Siculus, Beroſus,</hi> &amp; <hi>Moyſes</hi> alſo, certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doe report.) Vnto him alſo the people of Lybia conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated many triumphes, ceremonious obſervances, and generall feaſts, as one for his valour and vertues honored and worſhipped amongſt them as a mighty and powerful god: ſo were they blinded from the true ſight and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of knowledge, in thoſe times of darkneſſe, error, and ſuperſtition. And theſe people were firſt called Phutei or Phaetontei, as <hi>Ioſephus</hi> and <hi>Iheronimus</hi> in his tenth chapter upon the booke of Geneſis affirmeth. Vnto this <hi>Hercules</hi> of Lybia were adjoyned alſo all theſe names (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Aegyptian tongue) <hi>Her, Hercol, Arno, Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarno,</hi> and <hi>Ar;</hi> of which, hereafter occaſion will preſent it ſelfe, further to expound, and more largely to ſpeake of: but it is moſt unfallibly certaine, that this <hi>Hercules Egipti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> or <hi>Libicus,</hi> was long before the times of the ſo much renowmed <hi>Hercules</hi> of Greece: who indeed according to the writings of very many grave and learned authors, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved not the leaſt part of ſo many glorious praiſes and titles of honour, as the flattering and ſelfe-pleaſing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits of the Grecians have ſo amply and prodigally aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribed unto him: for he is by many authors ſet downe no other but a very pyrate on the ſea, a robber and bloudie oppreſſor, where he could find out any bootie or advaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to ſhew his power, wil, and mightineſſe; much unlike the proceedings that victorious and vertuous conqueror <hi>Hercules</hi> of Lybia: to approve which to be no detraction, but memorious notes of forepaſſed learned writers, <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nethon</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:9480:35"/>
that famous Prieſt and Hyſtorian of Aegypt, thus ſayth: <hi>Conſtat hunc Herculem Graecum dolo non bello Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medontem nil eiuſmodi, ſuſpicantem occidiſſe, &amp; primum ex maximis piratis extitiſſe, quanquam virum divino &amp; admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabilirobore preditum, &amp;c.</hi> Whereby it is very apparent by this authoritie and many others of like worth and anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, that this <hi>Hercules</hi> the Grecian was but ſome fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous robber or pyrate, living for the moſt part among the Argonauts, men excelling in warlicke diſcipline, and armed with armours of yron and other like furnitures for the wars, as <hi>Euſebius</hi> ſayth: <hi>Hercules Alceus affuit domito jam orbe, &amp; legibus &amp; regibus formato, &amp; instituto, &amp; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midoloſo ferro invento:</hi> wheras contrariwiſe, <hi>Hercules Egip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> lived in times of ignorance, in reſpect of thoſe know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, when the uſe of armour or yron was unfound out, the furie of warre not then felt, and in times of new-riſing tumults, not as then ripened or growne to any head or maturitie. His armour was the skins of wild beaſts, and ſuch like accouſtrements was he habited with: which alſo is attributed unto <hi>Hercules Alceus,</hi> as having a Lions skin and a great club in his hands, but they are among the reſt of the fables which the Grecians uſed, inſerted: for it is nothing likely, that the uſe of yron beeing in thoſe times found out, he would have uſed any ſuch inferiour meanes of defence for the ſafetie of his bodie. This aſſertion alſo maketh cleane contrarie againſt him: for <hi>Hercules</hi> of Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bia was borne before the deſtruction of Troy (according to the computation of the Aegyptian yeares) above tenne thouſand yeares, but <hi>Alceus</hi> not fully two thouſand, as <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odorus</hi> in his firſt booke of Time alleadgeth: which man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of computation and reckoning of the Aegyptians, if
<pb facs="tcp:9480:35"/>
we wil reduce to the order and rule obſerved by the Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deans, Scythians, Hebrewes, and Ianigenae, which is by the circular circumference and revolution of the Sunne, accounting it as we now reckon, we ſhall find, that he was borne preſently after the king of Babylon called <hi>Ninus,</hi> which is according to our latter obſervation, ſome eight hundred yeares before the overthrow and ruine of Troy; which maketh up the number &amp; proportion of ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand yeares, held and obſerved among the Aegyptians: by which we may perceive the great diſtance of time that was betweene theſe two famous perſonages, <hi>Hercules E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giptius</hi> or <hi>Libicus,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Oſyris,</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Iupiter Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus,</hi> and <hi>Hercules Graecus</hi> or <hi>Alceus</hi> (or as ſome hold) the ſon of <hi>Amphitrio</hi> and <hi>Alcmena:</hi> or the ſon (by adulterous meanes) as ſome others doe thinke, of one called <hi>Iupiter Graecus.</hi> But having now thus farre digreſſed from the maine entendement, wee will returne to the proſecuting thereof.</p>
            <p>The continuance of the raigne of the above written <hi>Iubalda,</hi> king of Spaine, dured from the foure and thirtith yeare of the raigne of <hi>Semiramis,</hi> the Babylonian Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe, untill the eighteenth yeare of <hi>Arius;</hi> which is in the whole about the time of threeſcore and foure yeares, as by the diligent &amp; carefull collections both of <hi>Euſebius</hi> and <hi>Beroſus,</hi> is clearely approoved. And about this time (the Patriarke <hi>Abraham,</hi> beeing about the age of a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares) is borne his ſon <hi>Iſaack,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſaack</hi> born.</note> as all hyſtories for the moſt part give record and mention. In the governement of this king <hi>Iubalda,</hi> no memorable act done in that coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, is left written by hyſtorians.</p>
            <p>Vnto the kingdome of Spaine, next after him, ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb facs="tcp:9480:36"/>
               <hi>Brygus,</hi> which was in the eighteenth yeare of the late ſpecified <hi>Arius,</hi> the Babylonians ſixt king; which is from the firſt inhabitation of Spaine, two hundred threeſcore and ſeven yeares, and before the foundation of Troy four hundred and thirtie. This word <hi>Brygus</hi> with the Arame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans and Armenians, is called Caſtellum. And the Etruſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans at this day (with whome many words of the Aramen language remaine) call a caſtle Bricola, by changing the letter g into c. This king <hi>Brygus</hi> (as <hi>Beroſus</hi> &amp; other writers affirme) founded and erected many townes and great ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles in the kingdome of Spaine, as <hi>Ptolomie</hi> alſo copiou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly hath delivered; as in the countrey of Luſitania, there are caſtles called at this day Laccobryga, Mirobryga, and others. And in the province of Taracona, a towne called Brygantum, Volubryga, and many others, ſounding and ending after the name of the king <hi>Brygus. Plinie</hi> ſayth in his fift booke of naturall hyſtorie,<note place="margin">Plinie.</note> that many old writers do affirme, That a certain people called Brygi in Europe travelled into Aſia, and there builded a citie and called it Brygios, which afterwards by chaunging the letter B into P, was called Phrygios; and that the Phrygians afterwards from theſe people tooke their firſt originall and being, of whome iſſued that famous progenie of the Trojanes, ſo gloriouſly renowmed throughout the world: and this king <hi>Brygus</hi> reigned in all ſecuritie and peace untill the firſt yeare of the reigne of <hi>Balaneus,</hi> the eight king of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon, which was about two and fiftie yeares or near ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts.</p>
            <p>The fift king of Spaine was <hi>Tagus</hi> (as <hi>Beroſus</hi> and <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorus</hi> deliver) and he began his rule and government be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the nativitie of Chriſt a thouſand eight hundred
<pb facs="tcp:9480:36"/>
threeſcore and five yeares, before the building of Troy threeſcore and eighteene yeares, after the firſt peopling of Spaine three hundred and nine yeares. And of this kings name that far-famed river Tagus taketh her name: in which (as <hi>Plinie</hi> and <hi>Solynus</hi> report) were found many golden ſands, heaped together in many places of that ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. This king with many authours is called alſo <hi>Tagum Orma,</hi> and <hi>Moyſes</hi> by ſynoereicall compoſition, tearmeth him <hi>Tagorma,</hi> as <hi>Ptolomie</hi> and many other writers of great worth and credite, more particularly have ſpoken of the ſame: and this <hi>Tagus</hi> reigned in the kingdome of Spain, about the time of thirtie yeares, by all due computation and conferring of conſent of times, and as <hi>Beroſus</hi> affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the ſame.</p>
            <p>In the firſt yeare of the reigne of <hi>Armatritis</hi> the ninth king of the Babylonians and Aſſyrians, the rule and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernement of the kingdome of Spaine fell and came un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Betus,</hi> of whom afterwards a great part of that country tooke her name, and was knowne by the name of Baetica. The Etruſcians by tranſpoſition and diviſion of ae, cal him <hi>Beatus,</hi> which with the Latines ſignifies happie or bleſſed. The Hebrewes derive this word Betus from Behin, which as S. <hi>Ierome</hi> interprets it, meaneth as much as, <hi>locus vitae meae (id est) foelic tatis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ptatae:</hi> and from hence it is likely, that in this countrey ſome ſuppoſed the Eleſian fields to be, and ſo alſo thereby many other ſuch like ſuppoſitions aroſe, which to decide, would here bee tedious, and too much digreſſion from the matter entended. This king <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> raigned ſeven and thirtie yeares, as <hi>Beroſus</hi> and other authors doe alleadge.</p>
            <p>After him in the eight and thirtith yeare of <hi>Armatritis</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:9480:37"/>
above mentioned, <hi>Gerion</hi> (ſurnamed <hi>Aſer</hi>) challenged un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him the rule and domination of the countrey of Spain: wherein it is written, he governed with great tyrannie and oppreſſion of the inhabitants thereof, intruding himſelfe by violent and forcible means into the poſſeſſion and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernement of that kingdome. This word <hi>Gerion</hi> ſignifies in the Hebrew tongue as much as <hi>advena</hi> in Latin, which he manifeſted more plainely by comming from Maurita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia into this kingdome of Spaine, and ruling there like a ſtraunger, according to his owne will, deſire, and mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. <hi>Beroſus,</hi> as alſo <hi>Diodorus Siculus,</hi> doth affirme, That he had another name alſo, which in the Aramen &amp; Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritanian language was <hi>Deabo,</hi> in the Greeke <hi>Chryſeo,</hi> in Latine <hi>Aureo,</hi> which firſt of all came of his great wealth and ſtore of gold, in which he moſt wonderouſly aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in thoſe daies: and this <hi>Gerion</hi> reigned thus in this his uſurped authoritie untill the eight and twentith yeare of the raigne of <hi>Belochus,</hi> the tenth king and ruler of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylonia, which was about the time of three &amp; thirtie years or near therabouts. Immediatly after him, three brethren together tooke the rule and government of this countrey of Spaine into their hands, which were called <hi>Deabi Lom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimi,</hi> which word (as S. <hi>Ierome</hi> expoundeth it) ſignifieth the cheefes or rulers of armies, and which wee call by the name of the three <hi>Gerions,</hi> beeing indeed the ſons of the beforementioned <hi>Gerion,</hi> the laſt king and ruler of Spain. In the time when theſe three brethren thus reigned and ruled together, happened that generally known accident, which afterward the world ſo univerſally entertained from the report of loud-tongued Fame, which was, the untime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and unfortunat death of <hi>Oſyris,</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Iupiter Iuſtus;</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:9480:37"/>
who was moſt traiterouſly and vilely murdred by his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Typhaeus Egiptius,</hi> whoſe all-lamented death was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward highly revenged by his ſonne <hi>Hercules Lybicus,</hi> who inſtantly took up armes, and ſcoured almoſt all the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries of the world, untill hee had found out the authour of the murther of his father <hi>Oſyris,</hi> upon whoſe bodie, his angrie and wrathfull mind tooke in the end direfull and cruell revenge: at which time alſo (hee beeing in the pride and fulneſſe of furie and choller) ſearcht out all corners and places of abode, where any ſuch like bloudie and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious gyants, rulers, and commaunders, kept their tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall and uncivile governments: among the reſt, he ſlew <hi>Buſyris</hi> in Phoenicia, <hi>Typhaeus</hi> the younger in Phrygia, <hi>Mylinus,</hi> a great commaunder on the ſea in Crete, <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theus</hi> in Lybia, the <hi>Leſtrigones</hi> in Italie, and afterwards, theſe three bretheren called <hi>Geriones</hi> in Spaine, and alſo many others in many other places, as hath alreadie here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore beene ſpoken of. After the overthrow thus of theſe late ſpecified <hi>Geriones,</hi> hee eſtabliſhed and appointed to ſucceed them one called <hi>Hiſpalus,</hi> who now after theſe, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly tooke upon him the government thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hiſpalus</hi> therefore (according to the report and affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of <hi>Beroſus</hi>) now entered to take poſſeſſion of the regaltie and principalitie of Spaine, which was from the floud five hundred foureſcore and nine yeares, before the erection of Troy two hundred one &amp; fortie years, before the birth of Chriſt a thouſand ſeven hundred twentie ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and after the firſt finding out and peopling of Spain three hundred ſeven and fortie yeares. Of this <hi>Hiſpalus,</hi> the citie Hiſpalis firſt was erected and ſo entearmed, and he was the ſonne of <hi>Hercules Lybicus,</hi> as many authours
<pb facs="tcp:9480:38"/>
and writers of fame and great antiquitie have given in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port unto the poſteritie of time. Hee reigned and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded over Spaine untill the very end of the reigne and governement of <hi>Baleus,</hi> the Babylonians eleventh king which was by juſt reckoning and account, the time of ſeventeene yeares.</p>
            <p>In the firſt yeare of the raigne of <hi>Altades,</hi> the twelfth king of Babylonia, <hi>Hiſpanus</hi> the nephew of <hi>Hercules,</hi> was eſtabliſhed king and ſole ruler over the dominions of Spaine, of whome the countrey then generally was called Hiſpania, which the mallice of time hath not yet worne out, but ſtill it is knowne and called after the ſame name. After him, <hi>Hercules</hi> (comming out of Italie, fraught with yeares and many victories) tooke upon him by the electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ſuffrages of all the people, the rule &amp; government thereof. And thus hath been lineally drawne foorth the firſt inhabitation of the countrey of Spaine with the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular and right ſucceſſions of the kings and commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders thereof, as hath been warranted and allowed by wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of great antiquitie and induſtrious Chronographers of Spain: where we will now ſurceaſe to wade any further, having brought it unto the very times where wee laſt left our cheefe purpoſe and matter; and will goe forward, and proceed from hence untill wee ſhall nearer arrive at the time wherein Troy was firſt erected and founded, following herein the ſame manner of method and forme, with which wee firſt ſet forth, and meane to continue unto the end (by the favourable permiſſion and allowance of the divine Majeſtie.) <hi>Hercules</hi> therefore ruling thus in Spaine, built and erected many goodly cities and faire caſtles in that countrey, wherupon at this day in ſome auncient re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords
<pb facs="tcp:9480:38"/>
and monumentall ſchedules of Spaine, you may read of another title given unto him, which is, <hi>Hercules edificator.</hi> He was called alſo by theſe names, as <hi>Her, Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>col, Arno, Muſarno:</hi> and they thus ſignifie and are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhed from the Hebrew tongue, as S. <hi>Ierome</hi> and others expound it: <hi>Her</hi> ſignifieth hairie, <hi>Hercol</hi> all covered over with haire, <hi>Arno</hi> ſignifieth a Lion, and <hi>Muſarno</hi> the por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traiture or effigies of a Lyon, and theſe names were thus aſcribed unto him, for that he alwaies wore for his upper garment the hairie skins of Lyons, Beares, Leopards, and other ſuch like beaſts, and for that on his ſhield or tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guet was depainted and drawne the ſhape and forme of a Lyon, and which, in all his wars and attempts hee alwaies caried about him: &amp; with ſome he was called the knight of the ramping Lyon. The town of Vetulonia, called alſo Viterbe, cauſed the picture of <hi>Hercules</hi> to bee ſtamped and imprinted on their coine: which continued unto the time of the raigne and governement of the laſt king of the Lumbards, who then abolliſhed the remembrance therof by any ſuch repreſentation or means of memorie. After the time of ſome nineteene yeares or thereabouts, as moſt writers doe alleadge, having governed with all love and obedience of the people, <hi>Hercules</hi> died, leaving all thoſe countries thereabouts heavily lamenting the loſſe and departure of ſo noble and gallant a conqueror; which was about the time of his owne age three hundred and fiftie yeares, and after he had reigned and commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in Fraunce, Italie, and Spaine, threeſcore and ſeven yeares. In ſolemne remembrance of whoſe generally deplored death, the people of Spaine erected many muſt ſumptuous and coſtly monuments, and beſtowed upon
<pb facs="tcp:9480:39"/>
him a wonderfull rich and ſtately tombe, which as ſome hold, was built hard by that place, which as wee now call them, the Gades, pillars, or columns of <hi>Hercules</hi> are ſeated upon, being not far from the famous ſtreights of Gibral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar. Vnto him alſo after his death they attributed very godlike honors, and tearms of veneration and reverence; ſo was hee poſſeſſed while hee lived among mortals, with the love and opinion of all thoſe people therabouts, and whereſoever elſe he had governed and commanded. And more of this ſo far renowmed conquerour <hi>Hercules</hi> ſhall not at this time bee declared, whoſe victories, triumphes, &amp; exploits would indeed require a ſmall volume of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, being ſo many, ſo glorious, &amp; ſo worthie, deſerving in the perfection of their owne merit to be inſculpt in the braſſe leaved booke of time-reſiſting and endleſſe perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuitie. And now we will revert our pen to ſpeake of his two famous ſons, <hi>Tuſcus</hi> king of Italie, and <hi>Galatheus</hi> king of Fraunce, and of their iſſue and poſteritie. But firſt is to be underſtood, that unto the kingdome of Spaine next after <hi>Hercules,</hi> ſucceeded <hi>Heſperus,</hi> beeing the twelfth king and governor thereof, &amp; who was brother unto the renoumed <hi>Atlas,</hi> whome hereafter occaſion will bee preſented to ſpeake and entreat of.</p>
            <p>It hath been before declared and mentioned, how that the great Monarch and Emperour <hi>Hercules</hi> diſpoſſeſſing himſelfe voluntarily of two royall &amp; mighty kingdomes, placed and inſtituted therein his two ſons, <hi>Tuſcus</hi> and <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latheus:</hi> who long time after lived reciprocally, &amp; reigned together in their ſeverall commaunds and governement, in all peace, quiet, and tranquilitie. And to ſhew and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt this their love and agreement the more, <hi>Tuſcus</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:9480:39"/>
freely beſtowed and gave unto his brother <hi>Galatheus</hi> the great Iſland of Sicilia, as then appertaining &amp; belonging unto the crowne and kingdome of Italie, and which was then altogether deſolate and diſinhabited (the race and generation of <hi>Cham, Noes</hi> ſon, the firſt commander ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, being now extinct and periſhed.) Vnto this Iſland, <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latheus</hi> made a journey, carying with him great numbers and abundance of people, and all things neceſſary for the in peopling and inhabiting thereof: which people and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he afterwards and from thence forth called after his owne name Galath-enes; and erected and built alſo a very great citie there, calling it by the name of Cenegalatha, of which citie likewiſe, <hi>Plinie</hi> in his fourth booke of Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall hyſtorie doth there entreat and mention. And it was held in thoſe daies to be the greateſt and cheefeſt honour that might bee, to authoriſe and licenſe any to build and erect any citie, and to call it after his owne name: for the denominating of which, no man neither could give any leave or authoritie, but thoſe which were eſtabliſhed in place and office of Coritus, that is, the Patriarke, <hi>Iupiter,</hi> or cheefe king and commander of that country, as <hi>Tuſcus</hi> then was, being the ſole king and ruler over all Italie and all thoſe territories adjoyning thereunto. And this grace and favour <hi>Galatheus</hi> tooke in great thankefulneſſe and all kind acceptance, endevouring by all means poſſible to be found gratefull for ſo high a favor received. After all mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters were well ſetled and orderly diſpoſed in this new ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted governement of Sicilia, <hi>Galatheus</hi> returned backe againe into his countrey of Fraunce, where with all ſigns and apparent tokens of a long wiſhed welcome, hee was joyfully received of his people in all the provinces round
<pb facs="tcp:9480:40"/>
about, where we muſt now leave him for a while, to ſpeak of his brother <hi>Tuſcus,</hi> and of his affaires and negotiations in his governement and charge.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Tuſcus</hi> (as is before declared) was the ſole and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute King, Patriarke, and <hi>Iupiter</hi> of all the dominions of Italie; of whoſe name alſo a cheefe province of that king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome then tooke her name, and was called Tuſcania, and by the favourable good will of the tyrant Time (who is wont to blot out all reliques and tokens of antiquitie) it yet retaineth the ſame: in which particular countrey, hee for the moſt part made his continuall abode &amp; reſidence, which before that time was called Etruria,<note place="margin">The diverſe and ſeverall names of Italie.</note> &amp; before that, Ianicula, and the people thereof Ianigenes, which is as much to ſay, as the iſſue of <hi>Ianus:</hi> it was alſo called Oeno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tria, Heſperia, Apenina, and many others, according to the greatneſſe or will of any ſuch cheefe or famous king ſo commaunding and ruling over it. <hi>Dionyſius Halicarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaeus,</hi> writeth, That the countrey Hetruria (taken often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times for the whole and entire kingdome of Italie) was alſo called Comera, of <hi>Comerus, Iaphets</hi> ſon; and it had to name alſo Razenua,<note place="margin">It was alſo called Tauri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnia.</note> Thuſcia, and Thuſſa, and at this day Italia, as hereafter ſhall be declared. <hi>Beroſus</hi> further ſayth, That at the firſt peopling and inhabiting thereof, it was called Vmbria of the people Vmbri, which heretofore we have ſomewhat touched, as alſo Pelaſgia of the people Pelaſgi (taken alſo ſometimes for the inhabitants of a countrey in Greece.) Beſides all theſe, it was alſo knowne by the name of Tarrhenia, as many authors of great and approved knowledge in matters of antiquitie, have more amply delivered, which opinion alſo ſhould be more eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly entertained, if wee will but diligently marke the diverſe
<pb facs="tcp:9480:40"/>
and ſeverall names given &amp; attributed unto other coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, after the ſame faſhion and manner: for firſt concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the people of Fraunce,<note place="margin">The old names of the people of Fraunce.</note> they were firſt of all called Samothei, of <hi>Samothes</hi> their king, then Celti, then Gala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tij, after that Belgae, of their king and Patriarke <hi>Beligius,</hi> after that Galli, and ſince that Francigenae or Franci. The names in like manner of the people of Germanie varied and differed very often and ſeverally:<note place="margin">The names of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manie.</note> For the firſt name that ever that people received, were Tuyſcones, of <hi>Tuyſcon</hi> one of <hi>Noes</hi> ſonnes, the firſt that ever was king and ruler over that country. After that they were called Gambrivij, then Ingheones, after that, Iſteones, Suevi, and Vandali, then alſo Thetanes, Theutontes, Vindelici, Vandaliſci, after that Alemanni, and laſt of all, of the Romanes (as ſome hold) they were generally entearmed Germani. So that by theſe it is plainly ſhown, how almoſt all countries and nations have at diverſe times been diverſly and diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringly called: by the occaſion of which, many writers that have not indeed ſeriouſly and laboriouſly lookt into frag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of old and authentike fathers, for the derivations and firſt originals of cities and countries, have beene infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with ſome diſeaſe or other of ignorance and errour; by reaſon of which daungerous ſickeneſſe, firſt creeping (though not perceived) into the heads of men learned and of authoritie, it hath prooved univerſally mortall, to all thoſe that have not invoked the aid of that good Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician, Induſtrie, throughout all the world whereſoever. And ſo now againe wee will returne to the place from whence we laſt of all ſet forth, which was from the matters and particulars which we handled of king <hi>Tuſcus,</hi> ſole ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler and commaunder of all the countrey of Italy, of whoſe
<pb facs="tcp:9480:41"/>
actions or memorable atcheevements, there is little read in any authors, onely it is writ, that hee firſt invented the order and dignitie of the Palladian knighthood, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted large priviledges and allowances for the maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of that new found ceremonie. And of any matter elſe which might challenge unto it ſelfe worth and extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarie commends, done and performed by him, few or no hyſtorians have written: onely hee left after him, his ſon <hi>Altheus</hi> inheritor &amp; rightfull ſucceſſor to his govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and kingdome.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Altheus</hi> then, the ſon of <hi>Tuſcus,</hi> began to take upon him the rule and commaund of Italie, preſently after the death of his deceaſed father, which was the fourth yeare after the death of his grandfather <hi>Hercules</hi> in Spaine, who as you have heard, left inheritour unto him <hi>Heſperus,</hi> the brother of <hi>Atlas,</hi> for the governement of that countrey: which <hi>Heſperus</hi> had not there long reigned, but hee was expulſed and driven out of his countrey by violent and oppreſſive meanes by his brother <hi>Atlas</hi> the gyant, ſurna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Italus:</hi> ſo that now hee was enforced to forſake the countrey, and to flie into Italie, in one part of which, hee afterward commaunded, and called it after his own name Heſperia, which name it long time afterwards retained. After this, <hi>Atlas Italus,</hi> not contented ſufficiently with the principalitie and dominion of Spaine (as overambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly thoughted) came alſo into Italie, and overſwayed by his mightineſſe and power al the country round about, and created and eſtabliſhed himſelfe king &amp; ruler therof, and called all the countrey generally after his owne name, Italia, by which it is at this day called, &amp; in the kingdome of Spaine he appointed one of his ſonnes to reign called
<pb facs="tcp:9480:41"/>
               <hi>Sicorus,</hi> which was now by juſt account the foureteenth king thereof. When theſe things were thus done, he went alſo into Sicilia, as <hi>Galatheus</hi> before had done, and there for a while he reſted himſelfe, till at the length he returned againe backe into Italie, wherin afterwards he lived many yeares. This <hi>Italus Atlas</hi> by his deſcent was of the linage of <hi>Iaphet,</hi> and of his ſonne <hi>Comerus Gallus,</hi> the firſt king of Italie; and it was hee, which according to the opinions of many, excelled moſt of all men then living, in the knowledge of Aſtrologie, for which cauſe, the buſie Poets fained, that he ſupported and upheld the heavens with his ſhoulders. <hi>Altheus</hi> all this while was ſuppreſſed and kept under by the mightineſſe of this ruler, by reaſon whereof, hyſtories cannot ſpeake of any worthie matter done or performed by him: onely it is written, he builded and ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted two very large and beautifull cities, one of them cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Alteta, the other Althea, with a caſtle alſo called after the ſame name. And this <hi>Altheus,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Tuſcus</hi> before ſpecified, was uncle unto <hi>Dardanus,</hi> the firſt builder and founder of Troy. Hee had alſo a ſonne called <hi>Blaſcon,</hi> but it is not read, that hee was afterward Coritus, that is, king of Italie, or commanded in any extraordinary power and authoritie; but that this <hi>Atlas Italus</hi> created and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed one of his owne ſonnes, called <hi>Morges,</hi> in the dignitie and office thereof, wrongfully diſinheriting the true heires that might lawfully have challenged the ſame: ſo that by this unjuſt meanes of uſurpation &amp; greatneſſe, the line and iſſue of <hi>Hercules</hi> was debarred from the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſing and enjoying of what rightfully belonged unto them. Alſo he created and appointed his daughter called <hi>Rhoma,</hi> as dutcheſſe and commaundreſſe of the people
<pb facs="tcp:9480:42"/>
and nation called Aborigines (of whome heretofore wee ſomething ſpoke of.) And this <hi>Rhoma</hi> was afterward ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to a prince of Tuſcane, of whom ſhe had a ſon called after her owne name <hi>Rhomaneſſos,</hi> who was the firſt that ever laid the firſt foundation of the citie of Rome; as <hi>Sem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pronius</hi> very confidently affirmeth, condemning all thoſe which attribute the firſt founding thereof unto <hi>Romulus,</hi> who (ſayth hee) indeed beautified and enlarged the ſame, but was not the firſt that laid the foundation thereof; and that his name <hi>Romulus</hi> (being himſelfe found hard by that cittie by wonderous accident) tooke his name of Roma, and not Roma of <hi>Romulus,</hi> as the above written authour <hi>Sempronius,</hi> a very ſufficient writer, and ſome others alſo of allowed authoritie, have averred the ſame. And the interpretation of this word <hi>Rhomaneſſos,</hi> as S. <hi>Ierome,</hi> the Talmudiſts, and many others doe expound it, is as much, as, <hi>Magna aut potens ſublimitas,</hi> a mightie or powerfull height or glorie; beeing compounded of two ſeverall words of the Aramean language; <hi>Roma,</hi> which interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſignifies <hi>ſublimitas,</hi> and <hi>Neſſon,</hi> which is <hi>validum</hi> or <hi>magnum:</hi> or as ſome underſtand it, it ſignifieth <hi>validum augurium,</hi> which is, a ſtrong and infallible prophecie, which indeed the exceeding greatneſſe &amp; all ſubjugating power &amp; mightineſſe of that Empire did afterwards very fitly anſwer and make good, being raiſed unto that infinit greatneſſe and higheſt perfection of ſoveraignetie, that it impelled almoſt the greater part of the world to ſue unto her for favour, and to become tributarie in great taxes and impoſitions unto her ſeat &amp; magnificence. And this citie alſo was called long after by the name of Valentia: of which, now wee will ceaſe further to entreat, returning to
<pb facs="tcp:9480:42"/>
the matter before handled of <hi>Atlas,</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Italus,</hi> now flouriſhing and commaunding over Italie in great puiſſance, glorie, and mightineſſe: who although (as it is alreadie before ſpecified) he bore great affection, favour, and love unto his ſonne <hi>Morges,</hi> and had eſtabliſhed him in the regaltie and kingdome of Italie, as Coritus, yet hee began in the end to thinke and meditat with himſelf how apparent and monſtrous wrongs and indignities hee had offered to all the iſſue and poſteritie of <hi>Hercules,</hi> in expel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling <hi>Altheus,</hi> and depriving his ſonne <hi>Blaſcon</hi> of his right in the principalitie of that countrey; &amp; in thoſe thoughts and humors, hee cauſed to be called unto him <hi>Camboblaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con,</hi> the ſonne of the beforementioned <hi>Blaſcon,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Altheus,</hi> and in lieu and recompence of all former and forepaſſed injuries, hee gave unto him one of his owne daughters in mariage and matrimoniall aſſociation, who was called <hi>Electra,</hi> with whome in dowrie hee gave all thoſe townes and countries lying about the Alpes and the hether mountaines, neareſt confining upon Italie: and upon this, preſently after died. After whoſe death, his ſonne <hi>Morges,</hi> poſſeſſed belike with holy and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous cogitations, acknowledging the mightie wrong and diſparagement which his father had impoſed on his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in law <hi>Camboblaſcon,</hi> in depriving him of his rightfull ſucceſſion, willingly and voluntarily deſpoiled himſelfe of his crowne and commaund, and transferred it upon <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boblaſcon,</hi> whom preſently hee cauſed to bee created and eſtabliſhed in the dignitie of Coritus, that is, the <hi>Iupiter</hi> or king of Italie; and ſo after that, contented himſelfe to live privately and obſcurely with his brother in law and ſiſter <hi>Electra:</hi> with whome hee had not many yeares lived
<pb facs="tcp:9480:43"/>
and converſed, but hee died, and paied Nature that debt which no ſureties can put off, or be bound for: and ſo then <hi>Camboblaſcon</hi> was with more generall allowances of the people fully inveſted in his office and place of Coritus, which is as much to ſay, as <hi>Iupiter Coronatus,</hi> as I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie made known, and which I cannot almoſt too often expound, in that many have made ſo many and ſeverall doubts and ſcrupules, What theſe <hi>Iupiters, Saturnes,</hi> and <hi>Hercules</hi> might meane? which names indeed are nothing elſe but titles of honour, ſuperioritie, and dignitie: and <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter</hi> was ſuch, as in Aegypt <hi>Pharoa,</hi> and in Rome <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and as now their Pope: for <hi>Iupiter</hi> is as much as, <hi>Iuvans pater:</hi> and <hi>Papa, Pater patrium.</hi> And whereas the ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious people in thoſe dayes honored and reverenced them as gods, it was nothing elſe, but for ſome excellencie and great dignitie they poſſeſſed, or for ſome great vertue, learning, and knowledge they were then endued with, as <hi>Fabius Pictor</hi> and <hi>Zenophon</hi> have delivered the ſame, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>Principes quia iuſti erant, &amp; religionibus dediti, iure habiti dij, &amp; dicti. Non enim arbitria illorum ab equo, vel populis à iure innato diſcedebant.</hi> Now then having ſatisfied that point, we may the more boldly proceed with our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendment and with the matters of this <hi>Camboblaſcon,</hi> king of Italie, and <hi>Iupiter</hi> and Patriarke thereof, and the great father (as they ſay) of the famous and renowmed Trojans. And this king built the faire cittie of Montoblaſcon in Tuſcania, which by corruption is now called and knowne by the name of Montflaſcon: and another alſo which hee named Coritus, now called Cornete, which is ſituated about ſome fortie miles from the now mightie cittie of Rome. And this <hi>Camboblaſcon</hi> had by his wiſe <hi>Electra,</hi> the
<pb facs="tcp:9480:43"/>
daughter of <hi>Atlas Italus</hi> king of Italie, three children, which are theſe, <hi>Iaſius, Dardanus,</hi> and <hi>Armonia: Iaſius</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing created Coritus and Patriarke of Italie, his father being alive, who alſo beſtowed upon him the rule and kingdome of Fraunce (as many hyſtoriographers affirm) the next yeare after; ſo that he became very mightie and powerfull in all thoſe countries thereabouts. And now we will proceed with the reſt of the kings of Fraunce, begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning where we laſt left of, which was (if it bee remembred) at <hi>Galatheus,</hi> the noble ſonne of <hi>Hercules</hi> of Lybia, and of his faire wife <hi>Galathea:</hi> where it was then mentioned, how this <hi>Galatheus</hi> at the hands of his loving brother <hi>Tuſcus,</hi> received the Iſland of Sicilia, and accordingly, caried with him people to inhabite and poſſeſſe the countrey, which being performed, he returned alſo back again into Fraunce, as hath been likewiſe before ſomewhat touched: after which time, hee lived peaceably and quietly many yeares, governing his people with great mildneſſe and clemencie, and yet mingled and accompanied with up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſſe of juſtice, and execution of his laws and edicts; of whoſe deeds and performances, more than are alreadie ſpoken of, few or no writers have mentioned, onely, that of him and of his name the countrey generally was called Gaule, and ſo continued, and the people therof tearmed Gaulons, which by corruption and overturning of many ages and times, are now in ſome part of that countrey called Wallons, and which before <hi>Galatheus,</hi> were called Samothei or Celti. And it is moſt likely by the conjectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall opinions of moſt writers, that this king <hi>Galatheus</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained and lived in thoſe dayes for the moſt part in that part of Gaule, which is now the province of Acquitaine,
<pb facs="tcp:9480:44"/>
which is ſo called of the abundance of waters and rivers, wherein that countrey was wont to exceed, and that this place was held to be the firſt and moſt auncient of all the other parts of Fraunce, which indeed are onely two more, for that the whole countrey of France is by moſt devided onely into three parts, and they are called Gallia Acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natica, Celtica, and Belgica, which of themſelves retaine and carie the very names of the firſt kings and rulers of them, as before is ſomething ſpecified. The cheefe citties and principall ſiegnories of Gallia Aquinatica,<note place="margin">The cheefe cities of Gallia Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinatica.</note> are ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and held to bee theſe, as moſt auncient writers doe conſent, Narbon, Thoulouſe, Caours, Rodetz, Lymoges, Perigort, Bourdeaulx, Zainctes, Augoleſme, Baione, Clermont, Bourges, Tours, Foix, Leſtore, Allebreth, Saint Pons, Nantes, Reſnes, Saint Malo, and others. The cheefeſt rivers and waters, theſe, Gironde, Dordonne, Garonne, Loire, Lalier, Cher, Charente, &amp; many others, now too long to recite.</p>
            <p>After the death of the famous and moſt renowmed prince <hi>Galatheus,</hi> his ſonne <hi>Harbon</hi> tooke upon him the governement of the countrey, and was eſtabliſhed the twelfth king of Fraunce, who preſently erected and built a very gallant cittie for his ſeat, and called it Harbonne after his owne name, which is now called Narbonne, as many authours doe affirme. And of this king, little or nothing is left written, memorable, or meriting a tedious commemoration or rehearſall: onely hee left behind him a ſon called <hi>Lugdus,</hi> which was now the thirteenth king of this countrey of Fraunce, and who built the famous citie called Lugdunum, called alſo Lyon; which is now one of the cheefeſt and principalleſt cities of France, and
<pb facs="tcp:9480:44"/>
which hath long time flouriſhed in great priviledges, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatives, and extraordinarie cuſtomes, beeing a citie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed treſ-auncient and of long continuance; and of her name, all that province is called Lyonnoiſe, which, as ſome hold, is contained within the bounds of Gallia Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tica, and is the greateſt and the cheefeſt part thereof.<note place="margin">The firſt foundation &amp; building of the cittie of Lyons in Fraunce.</note> And this citie of Lyons was firſt founded and erected by the ſame king <hi>Lugdus,</hi> in the twelfth yeare of the raigne of <hi>Mancaleus,</hi> the foureteenth king of Babylon, which is as much to ſay, as after the floud &amp; inundation of the whole world ſixe hundred and foureſcore yeares, after the firſt inhabiting of Fraunce five hundred and ſixteene yeares, before the foundation of the cittie of Troy one hundred and fortie yeares, and before the now famous citie of Paris was erected, two hundred and twentie years, before Rome was built, five hundred threeſcore and eighteene yeares, and before the incarnation and birth of our Saviour Chriſt a thouſand ſixe hundred ſeven and thirtie yeares, or neare thereabouts. And in the times of this king <hi>Lugdus,</hi> arrived and came into Fraunce the queene <hi>Iſis,</hi> who was ſo famous and ſo renowmed throughout all the world.</p>
            <p>After this <hi>Lugdus</hi> ſucceded his eldeſt ſonne <hi>Belgius,</hi> now the foureteenth king of that countrey, whoſe name is yet even freſh in all mens memories, for of his name that great and populous countrey called Gallia Belgica, tooke her title and was ſo called, of which (as of the other) we will now make ſome mention. The cheefeſt rivers and waters thereof are theſe, Leſcault, la Sambre, le Lis, le Rin, Meuſe, and Moſelle, Saine, Marne, Somme, le Daulx, and others: the cheefe woods and forreſts theſe, Mormault,
<pb facs="tcp:9480:45"/>
and Ardenne. The higheſt hils and mountaines, are the hill Saint Claude, les Faucſilles, and Voſegus. The prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall villages and greateſt citties are theſe: Cambray, Vallenciennes, Couloign, Conflans, Vtrecht, Mayence, Strasbourg, Aix, Conſtance, Lyege, Tournay, Arras, Amiens, Beauvais, Senlis, Laon, Noyon, Soiſſons, Meaulx, Rouan, Rains, Metz, Langres, Beſancon, Salins, Dole, Loſanne, Geneve, and Camberi. The cheefe ſieg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nories are theſe: the Dukedomes of Iulliers, Cleves, Cheldes, Brabant, Lorraine, Bar, Lembourg, and Luxem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourg: the counties Palatine, Haynau, Bourgoigne, Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retes, Montbeliard, Flaunders, Artois, Champaine, Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Zeland, and Namur. This king <hi>Belgius</hi> (of whome all theſe gallant and moſt famous countries were thus called) builded alſo the citie of Belges, of which, now only ſome ruines and reliques of memorie are left, which are to be ſeene in the countrey of Haynau, and which <hi>Iulius Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi> likewiſe in the ſixteenth booke of his Commentaries doth mention &amp; remember, where he calleth it Belgium. This word <hi>Belgius</hi> (as many old writers expound it) ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth in the Hebrew or Phenician language (which toung the ancient Gauloys then uſed) as much as, An auncient god wraſtling; for in thoſe times (as I alreadie have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken) the people called their kings, gods: by which it may be gathered, that this their king <hi>Belgius</hi> was a great wraſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, unto which kind of exerciſe and unto the barriers, the people inhabiting in Gallia Belgica did not long ſince wonderfully much addict themſelves, &amp; were very active and skilfull therein, howſoever at this day thoſe ſports for the moſt part are now utterly left off and rejected. S. <hi>Ierom</hi> ſayth alſo, That this word <hi>Belga</hi> ſignifieth in the Hebrew
<pb facs="tcp:9480:45"/>
tongue, An auncient commotion, or an old ſtrife: and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed heretofore thoſe people of that country were much converſant in wars, in troubles, and diſſentions, and were held to bee the moſt valiant and ſtrongeſt nation of this part of the world, as <hi>Caeſar</hi> alſo in his Commentaries al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadgeth to the ſame purpoſe, ſaying: <hi>Fortiſsimi autem omnium Belgi.</hi> And <hi>Strabo</hi> in the fourth booke of his Commentaries alſo ſayth thus: <hi>Omnium Gallorum Belgi ſunt ſummi:</hi> as a people that in thoſe times (as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten) could bring into the field three hundred thouſand fighting men. And thus much for the deſcriptions of the people of the countrey called Gallia Belgica, with the cheefeſt townes, ſiegnories, and rivers thereof, and now we will looke back again for the proſecuting and finiſhing of our former matter.</p>
            <p>In this king <hi>Belgius,</hi> the line and race of <hi>Galatheus</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Hercules Lybicus,</hi> failed and was determinate, ſo that upon his death the people of Fraunce (beeing of themſelves wonderfully deſirous to elect one of that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage ſo near as it was poſſible) beſtowed the government and commaund of that countrey upon the above written <hi>Iaſius Ianigena,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Iupiter Camboblaſcon.</hi> And ſo by that meanes <hi>Iaſius</hi> was inveſted and eſtabliſhed in that kingdome as the fifteenth king and Patriark thereof. And in this yeare the realm &amp; kingdome of Athens in Greece was firſt ſet up and begun, as <hi>Beroſus</hi> our cheefly followed author in theſe matters of antiquitie averreth, who thus ſaith: <hi>Apud Ianigenas à patre, Iaſius creatus eſt Coritus, &amp; anno ſequente ſimul ceperent duo reges, videlice primus Rex Athentenſium Cecrops priſcus, &amp; Iaſius Ianigena apud Celtas.</hi> And this was about foureſcore yeares or there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts
<pb facs="tcp:9480:46"/>
before the firſt building and erection of the cittie of Troy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iaſius Ianigena,</hi> the eldeſt ſon of <hi>Iupiter Camboblaſcon</hi> (as is before declared) beeing thus ſo gloriouſly poſſeſſed of two ſuch regall and powerfull kingdomes, and being in the cheefeſt ſpring and blooming daies of his age, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and joined in mariage with a noble and rich ladie called <hi>Ipitis Cibeles:</hi> for the celebration of which nuptials and eſpouſals, great feaſts and ceremonies of joy and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph were held and kept, and (as ſome write) performed in the cittie of Viterbe, then the capitall ſeat of all Tuſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia. And this was before the foundation of Troy three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore and ſeventeene yeares, in the preſence of <hi>Dardanus</hi> the firſt builder thereof, and brother to the new maried king <hi>Iaſius Ianigena.</hi> Many writers doe affirme, That in this mariage were greater triumphs, paſtimes, ſports, magnificencie, ſtate and pomp, than in any other in thoſe times throughout all the world whatſoever, and cheefely in reſpect of that noble aſſembly and meeting of ſo many mightie and great princes, and more particularly for the comming of the famous empreſſe and goddeſſe (as they tearme her) the Aegyptian <hi>Iſis,</hi> the daughter of <hi>Cham,</hi> the wife of <hi>Iupiter Iuſtus,</hi> otherwiſe called <hi>Oſyris,</hi> and the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of that all renowmed and ever memorable conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, <hi>Hercules</hi> of Lybia, king and emperor of all Fraunce, Italie, and Spaine. And this <hi>Iſis</hi> there firſt taught thoſe peple the manner of making bread, of floure, meale, and ſuch like ſtuffe; although before that <hi>Oſyris</hi> her husband had inſtructed them in knowledge of agriculture, tilling, and ſowing corne, yet they were not untill now perfected in the uſe and right applying thereof, eſpecially for the
<pb facs="tcp:9480:46"/>
making of bread, which they learned and underſtood by the comming of this empreſſe <hi>Iſis.</hi> And this mariage and ceremonie of aſſociation and matrimonie was the firſt that in thoſe times was celebrated and ſolemnized with any rites, feaſtivals, or new invented uſances, as <hi>Diodorus Siculus</hi> to the ſame purpoſe thus ſayth, theſe beeing his very words: <hi>Has nuptias à dijs primum celebratas ferunt, Cereremque in gratiam Iaſij ei ex frumento panem attuliſſe, Mercurium lyram, Palladem decantatum monile peplum, ac tibias, &amp;c.</hi> This their goddeſſe <hi>Iſis,</hi> otherwiſe called by the names of <hi>Ceres, Iuno, Frugifera, Legifera,</hi> and others, was by all probabilitie and by the opinion of all writers a woman of wonderfull long life and many yeares, for at her now arrivall and comming to this mariage into Italie, ſhe was at the leaſt foure hundred and fiftie yeares old, as ſhee that was borne in the firſt yeare of the raigne of <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miramis</hi> queene of Babylon, and lived in the whole at the leaſt ſix hundred and ſixteene yeares, for ſhee was living after the firſt deſtruction and deſolation of Troy, by the ſpace of fortie yeares or neare thereabouts, as almoſt all writers have delivered in their opinions to the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and effect. <hi>Iohannes Annius</hi> an old writer, ſayth, That ſhee was in Germanie in the time of <hi>Hercules Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mannus,</hi> the eleventh king of that countrey, by him called Almaigne: and <hi>Cornelius Tacitus</hi> alſo ſeemeth to affirme the ſame by theſe words, <hi>Pars Suevorum etiam Iſidi ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat.</hi> It is written alſo, that ſhe was in Fraunce in the time of <hi>Lugdus</hi> then king thereof, as hath beene before decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and that ſhee had travelled almoſt all theſe parts of Europe, inſtructing and teaching the poore ignorant people the uſe of many things then unknown &amp; unfound
<pb facs="tcp:9480:47"/>
out. And to approove the better that ſhe was preſent at this mariage of <hi>Iaſius Ianigena,</hi> it is yet apparent in that countrey of Tuſcan by many very auncient ſcrols, leſt ſtill from time to time in that countrey from one poſteritie to another; as alſo certaine old ſtatues and monuments of marble, with inſcriptions of characters infixed thereon, found out in the times of Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſixt, averre the ſame, which as <hi>Iohannes Annius</hi> ſayth, were firſt found in the earth in the citie of Viterbe: and that there were at that time upon further digging and ſearch of more ſuch like reliques, found hidden far in the ground four ſeverall images or pictures of triumph, the one was of <hi>Iaſius,</hi> the other of his mother <hi>Electra,</hi> the third of his faire ſiſter <hi>Armonia,</hi> which never maried, but continued and died a veſtall virgine, and the fourth was of <hi>Cibeles</hi> the now new maried wife of <hi>Iaſius.</hi> There was alſo found another ſquare kind of table made of marble, on which were in Greeke letters, theſe words following engraved, which not long after were thus tranſlated into Latine. <hi>Coritina deſponſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio, cum Electra Atlai Kytij iamdudum pertranſiverat, &amp; maxima Iſis Frumentaria atque Panifica, conceſsit ad nup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tias Iaſij filij Coriti, in habitaculum turrite Cibeles ſponſe Iaſij in prelio Cybelario, ad fontem Cybelarium, paulo poſt ſub vadimonia palatia, &amp; paulo poſt à ſcelerato fratre Dardano Iaſius male perijt in agro Iaſinello in Theiſijs, &amp;c.</hi> And theſe be the very words uſed heretofore by authors of antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. By theſe therefore and by like ſemblable apparences it is cleared, that this <hi>Iſis,</hi> their ſo reverently-adored god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſe, was now preſent at the conſummation of the eſpou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals of <hi>Iaſius Ianigena,</hi> king of Italie and Fraunce, with the ladie <hi>Ipitis Cibeles,</hi> his wife. And that this <hi>Iſis</hi> had travelled
<pb facs="tcp:9480:47"/>
and journeied through many and diverſe countries, it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by many and ſeverall pillars and ſtonie monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments erected in many countries of Europe in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, as many authours doe produce. <hi>Diodorus Siculus</hi> inferreth, That in Aegypt ſhee cauſed her ſelfe a mightie and ſtately columne to be erected, wherein ſhe cauſed alſo theſe words to bee inſculped and inſerted. <hi>Ego ſum Iſis Egipti Regina, à Mercurio erudita. Que ego legibus statui, nullus ſoluet: ego ſum Oſyrides, ego ſum prima frugum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventrix, ego ſum Oriregis mater.</hi> But to omit many other like authorities and approvements which might conduce to the clearer manifeſting and unclouding of what was firſt propoſed, wee will now goe forward with this royall mariage of <hi>Iaſius,</hi> that we with more ſpeed may attaine to the complete accompliſhment and effectuating of my purpoſed entendment.</p>
            <p>This great king and ruler <hi>Iaſius Ianigena</hi> had of this his wife <hi>Cibeles</hi> a ſonne called <hi>Corybantus,</hi> ſo that now there wanted not any terrene or earth-born delight or felicitie which might make this happie-ſeeming potentate more fortunat, mightie, or contentfull, but it is a common hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor of fortune, that amidſt the thickeſt and moſt abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dances of her graces and favours, ſhee in ſome angrie or fantaſticke imagination, ſuddainely ſnatcheth away her ſo liberally beſtowed gifts, and leaveth the late poſſeſſors thereof involved and wrapt in a world of the miſerableſt unhappineſſe and ſoule vexations that may be invented, as by the fatall ſucceſſe and end of this kings life moſt plainely appeareth. For when as <hi>Dardanus,</hi> his younger brother (a man indeed of a proud heart, great courage, and inward ambition) ſaw his brother <hi>Iaſius</hi> thus to float
<pb facs="tcp:9480:48"/>
(as it were) on the calme ſeas of joyous proſperitie, and to taſt of the ſweet cup of Nectar, which Fortune often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times adminiſtreth unto her favourites, and thus to live famous in ſuch abundant meaſure of grace and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; hee infinitely repined and malliciouſly ſtomacked ſuch the greatneſſe and height of his power and authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, he beeing himſelfe ſo ſuppreſſed and obſcured by the ſpight of Fortune, and living privately and without com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund, as an inferiour or ſome baſe born perſon or ſlave. Theſe things oftentimes revolving and ſtudying within himſelfe, he could not now any longer depreſſe or quench the overfurious heat of his aſpiring ſpirit, but in a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainefull and ſcorning kind of faſhion went unto his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the king, to demaund leave and licence, That (upon ſome occaſions of diſcontent pretended) he might depart out of the countrey to ſeeke out his better fortunes: which requeſt <hi>Iaſius</hi> refuſed to condiſcend unto, and would by no meanes allow of his brothers purpoſes in that behalfe intended: whereupon <hi>Dardanus</hi> (taking it in great diſlike and diſparagement unto his greatneſſe) began ſecretly to enter into deadly hoſtilitie with him, and to gather ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny factions and parties together on his ſide, which, by reaſon that he was exceedingly well beloved throughout moſt of thoſe countries, grew to a great number and mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of men, eſpecially of thoſe people then inhabiting on the other ſide of the river Tybre, which we called ſince the Latines, beſides the countrey of Naples, Povilla, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labria, and others thereabouts; all theſe conjoyned and conſorted with the faction of <hi>Dardanus:</hi> and with <hi>Iaſius,</hi> all thoſe on this ſide of Tybre, beeing them of Tuſcania, Fraunce, and other particular provinces thereabouts. At
<pb facs="tcp:9480:48"/>
this very time (as many writers doe deliver) happened in the world many uncouth, ſtraunge, and wonderfull por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, as fearefull earthquakes, lightening, blazing comets, and ougly viſions; as alſo throughout all Theſſalie a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall overflow and deluge of waters, in another part of Greece, a ſtrange combuſtion of houſes and townes, and miſerable effects of fire throughout moſt part of that countrey. In the ſame time alſo, <hi>Pharao</hi> king of Aegypt following <hi>Moyſes</hi> and the children of Iſrael through the red ſea, with all his armie periſhed and were overwhelmed with the churliſh buffetings of the angrie and wrathfull billowes. All which ſignes and extraordinarie accidents did manifeſtly pretoken &amp; prefigure the ſuddain approch of ſome great alteration of eſtates, and troubles of migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie kingdomes.</p>
            <p>The fire of diſcontent and enmitie betweene the two brothers beeing thus wholly ſet on flame, and diverſe at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts and meetings of wrath paſſed betweene them, it happened that <hi>Dardanus</hi> received the worſt, and upon many encounters ſtill was put unto his ſhifts, eſpecially by the freſh ſupplie and aid which <hi>Siceleus,</hi> king of the iſle of Sicilia, &amp; the ſixteenth king of Spain had then brought unto his brother <hi>Iaſius:</hi> ſo that continually being weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned more and more both in numbers of men, and in the courages of them that ſtaied, he was enforced for his own ſecuritie to give over thoſe ſuch publicke meanes of op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion and revenge, and to betake his thoughts unto contriving and plotting of ſome more inward and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore more daungerous ſtratagems. So that in the end (to avoid prolixitie and tedious circumſtance) he ſo wrought that he awaited a time when the king his brother (then all
<pb facs="tcp:9480:49"/>
ſuſpectleſſe of any intended miſcheefe) went privately to a fountaine or ſpring to waſh himſelfe, which occaſion and oportunitie ſo fairely preſenting it ſelfe, <hi>Dardanus</hi> moſt traiterouſly and vilely murdered him. And upon that, not daring to adventure his ſtay, or to engage him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſo far in thoſe caſes of perill, he preſently tooke ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping in the next haven, and with all his jewels &amp; what elſe riches portable, he could cary with him away, with many of his freinds, followers, and ſervitors, he ſecretly and cloſely ſet ſaile and departed.</p>
            <p>The right noble and treſpuiſſant king of Fraunce thus cruelly murdered by the bloudie hands of his owne natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall (though in that unnaturall) brother, in the fiftith year of his raigne and mightie governement, and in the four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore and fourth yeare of his owne age; all the people and inhabitants thereabouts began mightily to bewaile his untimely and miſerable end, which was before the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of Troy eight and twentie yeares or much therea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouts. In generall deploration and laments of this kings death, not only Italy and France, but all parts of the world unto whome the ſhrill voiced trumpet of Fame had ſounded forth this report, conjoyned and bemoned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, for that hee kept peace and amitie with all princes whatſoever, in all unitie, love, and concord; and carried himſelfe ſo upright and ſo wiſe in the troubleſome mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of affaires belonging unto two kingdomes, that hee gained and woon unto him the hearts and affections of almoſt all people whatſoever. After his death, his ſonne <hi>Coribantus</hi> ſucceeded in the governement of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Italie, but not of Fraunce, ſo that the people thereof were a good while after without a cheefe or ruler:
<pb facs="tcp:9480:49"/>
but in the end they choſe and elected one that was nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt unto the linage and line of <hi>Hercules</hi> as they might, and his name was <hi>Allobrox,</hi> now the ſixteenth king ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. The which king afterward for the moſt part kept and remained at the foot of the mountaines Apennini, afron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting upon Italie, and there commaunded even unto the hils Pyrenei (which divide the countrey of Spaine from France) and from the Mediterranean ſea unto the maine Ocean, and unto the river of Rhyne: and he there builded and erected many famous townes and citties, of which, ſome were thoſe which were ſince called Piemont, Savoy, Proavnce, Daulphine, and others, and which people of very late times (if not at this day) were called Allobroges: and in this kings raigne was the farre-famed and mightie citie of Troy firſt built and erected. To come unto the foundation of which, wee muſt here in theſe affaires pauſe and take breath a while, and returne unto <hi>Dardanus,</hi> now on the ſea toſſed with uncertaine fortunes, and tempeſt-beaten indeed with overblowing and cruell winds, ſo that he remained in very great daunger and hazard to bee caſt away and ſwallowed in the vaſt and mercileſſe embrace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the all-wracking waters. Enforced by theſe ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities, hee was glad to put in at an Iſland of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clades, attending there the favourable ſmiles of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, and the abatement of thoſe horrible and tempeſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſtormes. In the end hee put foorth againe, and recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the ſea Archipelagus, and went afterwards on ſhore in an Iſland in Greece called Samos or Samothrace, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that which the Poet <hi>Virgil</hi> in his eight booke of his Aeneidos ſayth: <hi>Arunculos, ita ferre ſenec his ortus
<pb facs="tcp:9480:50"/>
in agris, Dardanus Ideas frigiae penetravit ad urbes, Treici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amque Samum quae nunc Samothracia fertur.</hi> This Iſland of Samos or Samothracia, is directly oppoſite unto the countrey of Thrace in Greece where Conſtantinople is erected, which heretofore abounded in all plenteous ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner with Vines, Olive trees, Grapes, and others ſuch like fruit of moſt ſorts; and in this countrey alſo was the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and famous Philoſopher <hi>Pythagoras</hi> borne, and one of the propheteſſes called <hi>Sibeles Sameos:</hi> but it is now (the more to bee lamented) in the tyrannous hands and poſſeſſions of the bloudie and barbarous Turke. In this countrey, <hi>Dardanus</hi> ſtaied a good ſpace before he laid the foundation of Troy, hoping yet to bee recalled home a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine into Italie: but when hee perceived that all hopes were fruſtrate that were builded on ſuch grounds, hee put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth himſelfe foorth to ſeeke out as yet his further for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, which happened as hereafter ſhall breefely be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folded.</p>
            <p>It is to be underſtood, that on the other ſide of the ſea Helle ſponte, which is called alſo the ſtreights leading un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Conſtantinople, in the firme continent of a countrey called Aſia Minor, now called Natalia or Turkie, and not far from the above written Iſland of Samos, is a province called Lydia, which heretofore was called alſo Meonia; in the which countrey, as alſo in thoſe next and neare adjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thereunto called Phrygia, raigned and governed at that time a prince called by the name of <hi>Athus</hi> the youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, of the ſame bloud and parentage as was <hi>Dardanus</hi> for (if it bee remembered) we long ſince ſpake how <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cules</hi> of Lybia had a ladie to his wife called Omphale, by
<pb facs="tcp:9480:50"/>
whom hee begat a ſonne called <hi>Athus</hi> the great, of which <hi>Athus,</hi> from diſcent to diſcent in foure generations came this <hi>Athus</hi> the younger king of Meonia and Phrygia, and who had two ſonnes alſo, the one called by the name of <hi>Lydus,</hi> the other <hi>Tur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>henus.</hi> This king <hi>Athus</hi> having now upon the arrivall of <hi>Dardanus,</hi> great abundance of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in his countrey, by reaſon of fruitfull encreaſes and multiplications: and having alſo but ſmall ſtore of victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als and food in his countrey to nouriſh and maintaine ſo populous a ſtate, for want of which, great famines, peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lences, and other diſeaſes aroſe in the countrey, knew not almoſt how to diſpoſe of his people, or in what ſort to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie this miſcheefe, ſo that in the end hee was enforced by reaſon of that mortall famine, to diſcharge many of his ſubjects out of the countrey to ſeeke out ſome new inhabitations and places of abode: which thing alſo they wonderous willingly embraced as glad to be rid and quit of ſo penurious and ſtarving a place. <hi>Dardanus</hi> hearing and underſtanding of theſe proceedings, and in what ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities they ſtood in by meanes of the overaboundance of inhabitants, preſently made his repaire to king <hi>Athus,</hi> and there deſired of him, That ſince hee muſt needs ſend forth ſuch people for the finding out of new places of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitations, that he would beſtow the charge, conduct, and leading of them upon him, and that hee would joyne with them for the proviſions and neceſſaries needfull and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient for the ſetling of themſelves in ſuch their new places of abode, reſidence, and habitation. This thing king <hi>Athus</hi> very willingly entertained, eſpecially, for that <hi>Dardanus</hi> was of his owne kindred and conſanguinitie.
<pb facs="tcp:9480:51"/>
This requeſt and deſire of <hi>Dardanus</hi> thus obtained, hee knew no other meanes to requite ſo great a favour, and to bee occaſion to draw on further kindneſſes, but to offer unto <hi>Athus,</hi> and utterly to reſigne all his right, title, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terreſt, and claime in the kingdome of Italie for one of his ſonnes, unto which of them the father pleaſed and was contented. This profer of <hi>Dardanus</hi> beeing well conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of by king <hi>Athus,</hi> was in the end thankefully accepted: in lieu and exchaunge whereof was allowed unto <hi>Darda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> a certaine quantitie and peece of ground in Phrygia for him to build and erect a citie upon. And betweene the two brethren, <hi>Lydus</hi> and <hi>Turrhenus,</hi> lots were indifferent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly caſt, which of them with a certaine number of people ſhould ſet forward for Italie, and which ſhould ſtay at home: for the deciding whereof, it fell unto <hi>Lydus</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main behind, and to be left inheritor unto that kingdome which afterwards of his name was called Lydia; and that <hi>Turrhenus</hi> ſhould bee preſently diſpatched away with his people to inhabite in Italie, of whome afterwards alſo it was called by the name of Turrhena. Theſe covenants and agreements concluded upon, <hi>Turrhenus</hi> ſetteth for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward from Aſia Minor (now called Turkie) in his journey for Italie; and <hi>Dardanus</hi> with his people and aſſociats be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan now to build in Phrygia, and in ſhort ſpace fully finiſhed and erected a citie, which he called after his own name Dardania: which was before the incarnation of Chriſt a thouſand foure hundred foureſcore and ſeven yeares, before the building of Rome by <hi>Romulus</hi> foure hundred and ſeven and twentie yeares, and before the citie of Paris was erected threeſcore and tenne yeares, as
<pb facs="tcp:9480:51"/>
               <hi>Euſebius</hi> and moſt writers doe affirme. On the other ſide <hi>Turrhenus</hi> is arrived in Italie, and preſently repaireth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the queene <hi>Cibeles,</hi> the widdow and late wife to <hi>Iaſius Ianigena,</hi> as before hath been declared, as alſo unto her ſonne <hi>Coribantus</hi> king of Tuſcania; unto which two, hee brought and preſented many coſtly and rich gifts from his father <hi>Athus</hi> king of Meonia: who alſo received them in all gracious and kind acceptance, as comming from their kinſman, and of the race and bloud of <hi>Hercules</hi> of Lybia. <hi>Turrhenus</hi> had not long remained here, but that he was highly favoured of the king <hi>Coribantus,</hi> who now deſirous to ſee and underſtand of the eſtate of his kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>Dardanus,</hi> prepared preſently to take in hand that ſo long and tedious journey, and ordained and inſtituted at home for the governement of his countrey, the order of the twelve Dukes, whereof <hi>Turrhenus</hi> was one; and ſo with a great troupe and companie of followers &amp; friends he embarked for the coſt of Phrygia, to ſee the greatneſſe of <hi>Dardanus,</hi> and the beautie and excellencie of his new built citie Dardania. After ſome tedious and troubleſome travels in this voyage, at the laſt hee arrived at his wiſhed and deſired place, where with all manner of ceremonie he was joyfully entertained by <hi>Dardanus,</hi> whoſe recipro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call and mutuall love grew in the end to bee ſuch, as hee reſolved and there ſet downe his reſt for ever to remaine, and not to returne againe into Italie, but ſent word the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of his purpoſes, and commaunding them to create and eſtabliſh <hi>Turrhenus</hi> in his abſence king and ſole ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler over all that countrey. In few yeares <hi>Dardanus</hi> began to grow unto great mightineſſe, riches, and power, who
<pb facs="tcp:9480:52"/>
had alſo a neighbour prince, of mightie puiſſance, weal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie, and fortunate, whoſe name was <hi>Te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rus,</hi> whereupon many writers call the Phrygians alſo Teucri; and this <hi>Teucrus</hi> was the ſonne of <hi>Scamander</hi> and <hi>Idea,</hi> and had alſo himſelfe a very beautifull and faire daughter, which hee maried ſhortly after unto <hi>Dardanus,</hi> and was called <hi>Batea,</hi> of whome <hi>Dardanus</hi> begot a ſonne called <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ictho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius,</hi> who ſucceeded after him and was inheritour unto the kingdome of Phrygia. This <hi>Ericthonius</hi> in proceſſe of time aroſe up unto a wonderfull greatneſſe and large poſſeſſions, who (as many writers do affirme) was accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to bee one of the richeſt kings in thoſe daies in that part of the world, who (as it is alſo ſaid) had at the leaſt three thouſand horſes of his owne continually feeding in his paſtures. And this <hi>Ericthonius</hi> had alſo a ſonne whom he named <hi>Tros,</hi> whome after his death hee left as ſucceſſour and inheritour unto him, and of whoſe name afterwards the Dardanians were called Trojans. This <hi>Tros</hi> very much obliged and beautified the cittie alſo of Dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dania, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>; which long time after it retai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> had three ſonnes, which were, <hi>Ilus, Aſsaracus,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> hee brought up in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> warlicke ſciences, unto which kind of ſtudie (as it is written) hee himſelfe alſo was much addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, and had many yeares together maintained hoſtile warres with the king of Crete called <hi>Iupiter,</hi> the fourth of that name there: in which warres, his ſonne <hi>Ganimedes</hi> was taken priſoner even by the hands of <hi>Iupiter</hi> himſelfe, who for that in his enſigne and colours he gave an Eagle, (being his armes) it ſhould ſeeme the Poets for that cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:9480:52"/>
have deviſed and feigne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> as hee was on hunting was ſnatcht up from the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> unto heaven by <hi>Iupiter,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Eagle, find that hee is now taken for one of the twelve ſignes of the Zodiake called Aquarius. Some other authors alſo write, that one <hi>Tantalus,</hi> king of high Phrygia and of Paphlagonia, a moſt miſerable, covetous and auaricious prince, had laid certaine ſna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es and privie meanes to entrap this <hi>Ganime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des</hi> and to take him priſoner as hee uſed to ſport himſelfe in hunting, thinking by that deviſe to get a mightie raun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of his father <hi>Tros</hi> for the redeeming and enfranchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of his impriſoned and captivated ſonne, and that this <hi>Tantalus</hi> ſent him to one <hi>Iupiter</hi> of the Iſle of Crete, for to ſafegard him, and to have halfe the raunſome which ſhould bee paied for his redeliverie and freedome. And for ſuch like cauſes belike, the Poets alſo doe invent and ſay, that <hi>Tantalus</hi> is plagued and tormented in hell, ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding up to the chin in water, and apples hanging downe unto his lips, and yet can neither drinke nor taſt the one or the other; and it is alſo more credibly written, that he died moſt miſerably and in great extremitie. His ſonne <hi>Pelops</hi> alſo, baniſhed and exiled his owne naturall coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, fled into Greece, and there maried a wonderfull rich wife and great ladie, by which meanes hee got unto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and obtained the commaund of a whole countrey, which he called after his own name Peloponneſus, which is now the countrey of Mauritania, and ſubject unto the Empire of the Turke. And of this <hi>Pelops</hi> iſſued and came the two famous captaines, <hi>Agamemnon</hi> and <hi>Menelaus. Tros</hi> thus having loſt his ſonne on this faſhion, ſtudied
<pb facs="tcp:9480:53"/>
upon revenge, and in the meane times comforted him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with his two other ſonnes, <hi>Ilus</hi> and <hi>Aſsaracus.</hi> And this <hi>Ilus</hi> called Troy after that, Ilion; who begat a ſonne named <hi>Laomedon,</hi> the father of the renowmed <hi>Priamus:</hi> and of <hi>Aſſaracus</hi> iſſued and came <hi>Anchiſes, Aeneas</hi> father. And the before written <hi>Tros</hi> ruled &amp; commaunded there in great power and puiſſance for the ſpace of threeſcore yeares or neare thereabouts,<note place="margin">Archilochus.</note> as <hi>Archilochus</hi> in his booke of Times alloadgeth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laomedon,</hi> the ſonne of king <hi>Ilus</hi> (as is beforeſaid) after the death of his father tooke upon him the rule and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of Troy, in the two hundred and two and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth yeare after the firſt foundation therof by <hi>Dardanus,</hi> and hee had five ſonnes and two daughters, which were theſe, <hi>Priamus, Titonus, Lampus, Clytion,</hi> and <hi>Letaon,</hi> and of theſe <hi>Homer</hi> in his Iliads maketh further mention: his daughters were <hi>Antigone</hi> and <hi>Heſione.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Homer.</note> The Greeke Poets (who indeed for the moſt part are full of ſuch like fables) doe ſay, that the two gods <hi>Neptune</hi> and <hi>Apollo,</hi> for a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſumme of money promiſed them by him, went with him about the circuit of the citie, and there erected won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull ſtrong and moſt huge high wals round about the ſame: the which wals afterwards finiſhed accordingly, and no money received nor to bee got, <hi>Apollo</hi> in great rage and anger infected the citie with a deadly and generall pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilence; and <hi>Neptune</hi> in token of his wrath and diſpleaſure alſo, ſent a monſter of the ſea among them, unto which, they muſt every day give and throw a young child, or els that they all ſhould periſh and bee devoured by the rave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous maw and hunger thereof; and that in the end it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened
<pb facs="tcp:9480:53"/>
upon the daughter of <hi>Laomedon</hi> (called <hi>Heſione</hi>) to be given unto this marine beaſt, which (ſay they) was reſcued and releeved by great fortune by <hi>Hercules</hi> of Greece, which came that way, and who afterwards ſlew that monſter, and in gratification therof the ladie <hi>Heſione</hi> (the daughter of <hi>Laomedon</hi>) was promiſed unto him not long after in marriage, but yet not married unto him by reaſon of the unwillingneſſe afterward (howſoever it fell out) of her father: for the breach of which promiſe, <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cules</hi> afterwards ſlew <hi>Laomedon</hi> in open battell, and ſpoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and ruinated ſuch his glorious citie. And for that <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamon</hi> his conſort had that day behaved himſelfe very valiantly in fight, hee beſtowed the young ladie <hi>Heſione</hi> upon him, as his concubine and ſlave; who carried her away with him into the countrey of Solamina, whereof he was then king and ruler. But it is moſt certaine, that for the moſt part all thoſe Greeke writers have erred infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely and have delivered many moſt unlikely hyſtories: for this <hi>Hercules</hi> (as hath been before ſpoken) was a nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and a famous pyrate; and hee ſlew <hi>Laomedon</hi> by trecherie, and ſurpriſed Troy on a ſuddaine and unawares, and alſo hee was a common raviſher of maidens, as of <hi>Heſione, Medea,</hi> and others, as <hi>Manethon, Iohannes Annius,</hi> and <hi>Iacques de Bergame</hi> have written and very plainely approved the ſame. <hi>Laomedon</hi> beeing ſlaine, <hi>Titonus</hi> ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded next after him: but he being of another diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, reſigned his interreſt therein, and betooke himſelfe to travell into ſtraunge countries, even unto the Indies, where (according to <hi>Diodorus Siculus</hi>) hee maried a ladie called <hi>Ida,</hi> and (as the Poets write) <hi>Aurora:</hi> of whome, hee
<pb facs="tcp:9480:54"/>
afterwards had a ſonne called <hi>Memnon,</hi> who long after came unto the ſuccour of <hi>Priamus</hi> in his cheefeſt warres, and was there ſlaine by the hands of <hi>Achilles.</hi> In the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence therfore of his brother <hi>Tython, Priamus</hi> took upon him the government and charge of that kingdome, being the ſecond ſon unto <hi>Laomedon</hi> their father: who in ſhort time came to bee one of the greateſt and moſt famous princes of the world, for it is written, that he was wondrous wiſe, diſcreet, and valiant, and matcht his children with perſons of great ſort, worth, and dignitie. And for to make him at the firſt the ſtronger, and that he might have time to reedifie his late ſpoyled and fire periſhed cittie, hee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered into alliance and faſt kindred with a very mightie and powerfull prince, neare adjoyning upon his country, who was called by the name of <hi>Cypſeus,</hi> or (as ſome hold) <hi>Dymas,</hi> king and ſole commaunder of Thrace, which is a province in Greece on this ſide of the ſea Helleſpont, whereof the cheefe cittie is at this day Conſtantinople: and with this <hi>Cypſeus</hi> or <hi>Dymas</hi> his daughter, called <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuba,</hi> hee maried: a ladie accompliſht with all exteriour graces and inward vertuous diſpoſitions, at which eſpou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals of <hi>Priamus</hi> and <hi>Hecuba,</hi> great ceremonies and ſignes of joyfulneſſe were ſhowne foorth and obſerved: and of this ladie it is writ, that he begot nineteen children male and female: and of other women and concubines which he dayly kept and maintained in his pallace (according to the faſhions and uſances in thoſe daies) hee had one and thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tie more, ſo that onely nineteene of his fiftie ſonnes and daughters were legitimate and lawfully begotten, the reſt baſtards and illegitimate. That <hi>Priamus</hi> in all had ſo
<pb facs="tcp:9480:54"/>
many children (which indeed hee publickely maintained and ſhamed not to acknowledge) <hi>Virgil</hi> alſo in the ſecond booke of his Aeneidos thus ſayth: <hi>Quinquaginta illi thalami, ſpes tanta nepotum.</hi> And <hi>Homer</hi> likewiſe in the laſt booke of his Iliads moſt plainely ſeemeth to confirm the ſame.</p>
            <p>Troy now thus moſt gallantly flouriſhing, newly forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, repaired enlarged, enriched, enpeopled, &amp; throughly provided and ſtored of all manner of things which might bee neceſſarie either for the uſe of fatall warres and open hoſtillities, or for the conſervation of peace &amp; domeſticke tranquillitie, began to aſſume unto her ſelfe a mighty and glorious ſelfe-conceit and ſtrong opinion of her owne power, height, and magnificence, aſſuring her ſelfe of all victorious prevailements over her enemies whatſoever, and of a never failing proſperitie, glorie, and felicitie: and yet it is not writ, that <hi>Priamus</hi> himſelfe was puft up with any more extraordinarie pride or inſolencie than became the greatneſſe of ſo puiſſant a prince. It is writ alſo, that in the times of this his greateſt power, he was forewarned by certaine Oracles and falſe gods which they uſed to worſhip in thoſe daies, that ſo long as hee did preſerve and ſafegard three things belonging unto the cittie, the towne ſhould bee inexpugnable and never to bee loſt, as <hi>Servius</hi> and <hi>Boccace</hi> have written of the ſame; the things were theſe, The image of <hi>Pallas</hi> called Paladium, preſerved undefaced, The ſepulchre or tombe of <hi>Laomedon</hi> which was under the great gate Scea, kept undeſpoiled &amp; whole, and ſo long as the life of <hi>Troylus</hi> laſted and did endure. <hi>Priamus</hi> therefore very carefull to keep theſe three things
<pb facs="tcp:9480:55"/>
with all diligentneſſe and heed, lived in the greateſt pompe, delicacie, and ſtate that ever any prince in the world in thoſe times did or could: ſo that he ſeemed not onely to bee king of Phrygia, but alſo cheefe dominator and emperour of all Aſia, now called Natalia or Turkie: and hee was called alſo in thoſe times, The king of kings, as <hi>Strabo</hi> in the thirteenth booke of his Geographie, to the ſame purpoſe thus ſayth: <hi>Priamus magno ex parvo, &amp; Rex Regum effectus.</hi> And theſe his powers and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities not onely extended and ſtretcht themſelves abroad throughout the maine continent and firme lands of all thoſe countries thereabout round, but in the end ſhewed themſelves alſo and poſſeſſed their maiſter of many fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous and great Iſlands lying farre in within the boſome and embracement of the uncivile and rude behaviored ſea; as the Iſland of Tenedos, and the Iſland of Metelyn, were ſubject and vaſſalized unto the governement of his imperious principallitie, paying him yearely tributes, taxes, and impoſitions; and many others alſo of great ſame adjoyning neare thereabout: ſo that the infinite greatneſſe and large commaund of this thrice mightie emperour <hi>Priamus,</hi> poſſeſſed all the princes and rulers of countries neare that way, with aſtonied admiration and wonderous maze of his ſo ſuddaine and unexpected puiſſancie. And thereupon ſent and diſpatched meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers from all quarters to crave his amitie, friendſhip, and to be in league with him, as alſo to bee nearer allied unto him in ſome matches and marriages of their children on both ſides; by reaſon whereof, <hi>Priamus</hi> matched his children with great houſes, and of great power and
<pb facs="tcp:9480:55"/>
poſſeſſions. Firſt hee married one of his legitimate and lawfully begotten daughters called <hi>Creuſa,</hi> unto a prince of great meanes named <hi>Aeneas,</hi> the ſonne of old <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſes:</hi> his daughter <hi>Aſtyoche,</hi> hee matched with one <hi>Telephus,</hi> a mightie king of Myſia: and his ſonne <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor</hi> joyned in matrimonie with <hi>Andromacha,</hi> the faire daughter of <hi>Ection,</hi> the powerfull and famous king of Thebes and Silicia: and <hi>Polydamas,</hi> one of the ſonnes of <hi>Anthenor,</hi> married with one of <hi>Priamus</hi> daughters, (beeing a baſtard, and begotten of one of his concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bines) beeing of an excellent and ſingular beautie, called <hi>Lycasta.</hi> So alſo manie others of his children were linked and joyned in marriages with men of great rule, power, and commaund in thoſe dayes; the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteritie of which, and of their deedes and mightineſſe, hereafter in ſome other place and oportunitie, occaſion may bee preſented further to ſpeake of, And for this time (beeing indeed forced by an extraordinarie occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion) I muſt thus on the ſuddaine abruptly breake of; deſiring and wiſhing very earneſtly, that if this ſmall peece of paines of mine ſhall fortune ever to bee pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickely impreſſed (which leaving behind mee, it will not bee in my power to prevent) it may indifferently paſſe uncenſured, till the returne of his fortune beaten father may aunſwere for the innocencie of the child, and bee able a little better to protect him in his affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions.</p>
            <p>And thus it hath beene with great care and diligence laboured to find out the trueſt Hyſtorians for the deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb facs="tcp:9480:56"/>
of <hi>Dardanus,</hi> and conſequently this king <hi>Priamus,</hi> from the race and line of the firſt prince and Patriarke <hi>Noe,</hi> with the particular ſucceſſions of kings and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours of Europe, as hath beene warranted by the authorities and writings of very learned and authenticke authours.</p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <hi>Tempo è figliuola di verita.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:9480:56"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
